The Indonesian economy is forging ahead with accelerated growth underpinned by macroeconomic stability.  This accelerated performance is being fuelled by strengthening consumption, exports and investment.  Consumption is climbing on the back of buoyant consumer confidence, availability of consumer financing and low import prices. Alongside this, more robust export activity is being spurred by vibrant demand from China and India. The resurgent domestic and international demand has brought renewed growth in investment. In 2010, the Indonesian economy is forecasted to grow by 6.0%-6.3%, with growth in 2011 climbing to 6.0%-6.5%. In analysis of prices, inflation mounted significantly during Q3/2010. Price increases were recorded mainly in the volatile foods category, and particularly for seasonings and vegetables. Nevertheless, inflationary pressure from core items and administered prices stayed low. Bank Indonesia is keeping a close watch on this potential for inflationary pressure and is strengthening policy coordination with the Government at both central and regional levels. Bank Indonesia will respond with the necessary policy mix to keep inflation on track with the established target at 5%±1% in 2010.

The global economy remains on the path of growth, albeit at varying levels. The larger economies, notably the US, Japan and China, have entered a slowdown. The drop in US economic growth comes in response to pressure bearing down on consumption from high unemployment and the credit crunch, while in Japan, the economic slowdown is explained by appreciation in the yen that has dented export competitiveness.  China, where the economy had advanced at a rapid pace, has been compelled to apply brakes to avoid overheating.  On the other hand, Europe and particularly Germany and France have charted better than expected growth. This improvement has resulted in part from rising exports and results of stress testing of European banks that exceeded expectations, thus rekindling optimism among economic actors. Alongside this, emerging market economies continue to chart solid growth. Sustained expansion in global manufacturing and steadily rising volume of world trade helped the world economy to maintain growth during Q3/2010, although a more moderate level than in Q2/2010. 

The Indonesian economy is expected to post more robust growth for Q3/2010 compared to the preceding quarter. Growth in the domestic economy for the quarter is estimated at 6.3% (yoy). Key to this growth is buoyant household consumption, with estimated growth holding above 5% (yoy). The brisk pace of consumption is being fuelled by consumer optimism and higher incomes bolstered by export earnings.  Export growth in Q3/2010 is estimated at 11.4%. Exports have climbed as a result of the steady improvement in world economic growth, led by China and India, and the growing diversity of export destinations. Investment growth is projected at 9.9% (yoy) for Q3/2010, and comes in response to rising demand and improvement in the investment climate.  This condition also augurs for renewed growth in imports. In disaggregation by sector, growth in non-tradable sectors forged ahead of the tradable sectors.

The upbeat condition of economy is also reflected in economic gains in the regions. Regional economic growth was driven mainly by strong performance in the estates and mining subsectors in the Sumatra region and Eastern Indonesia (Sulawesi, Maluku, Papua collectively known as Sulampua).  In addition, the manufacturing and construction sectors generated significant contributions to economic growth in the regions of Java, Bali and Nusa Tenggara (Jabalnustra) and Kalimantan. On the demand side, regional economic growth has been fuelled by consumption and investment in response to buoyant consumer optimism, expanding consumption credit and stable farmer terms of trade. Investment is up in both construction and non-construction business Investment in construction is expanding at a brisk pace in Jakarta and the Jabalnustra region. In Jakarta, construction investment is focused on retail and office properties. Regarding exports, the rise in manufactured exports is contributed mainly by the Jabalnustra region and Jakarta. In contrast, expansion in resource-based exports has taken place in the Kalimantan, Sulampua and Sumatra regions despite crop losses from anomalous weather conditions. 

Regarding prices, inflation mounted steadily in Q3/2010, largely from pressure in the volatile foods category. The persistently high volatile foods inflation has been caused by anomalous weather conditions that have disrupted production and distribution as well as from a hike in household electricity billing rates. Added sources of inflationary pressure are hikes in tuition fees coinciding with the start of the new academic year and surging demand related to the religious festive season. Nevertheless, inflationary pressure in September 2010 eased to 0.44% (mtm) from 0.76% (mtm) one month earlier. Taken together, CPI inflation in Q3/2010 widened to 2.79% (qtq) or 5.80% (yoy) from the previous quarter inflation at 1.41% (qtq) or 5.05% (yoy). Despite this, administered prices had little impact on CPI inflation due to the absence of strategic government decisions regarding prices in September 2010.

In preliminary figures for Q3/2010, Indonesia's balance of payments surplus exceeded earlier forecasts. Key to this is significant improvement in the capital and financial account surplus. The steep rise in the capital and financial account surplus has been driven by improving international perceptions of the Indonesian economy, marked by upgrading of Indonesia's credit rating, upward trend in returns on rupiah investments and excess global liquidity. On the other hand, the current account is expected to post a reduced surplus in the wake of high import growth as domestic economic activity gathers momentum. Nevertheless, the dominance of imported raw materials and capital goods signals that the accelerated imports will continue to benefit domestic economic activity. Taken together, international reserves at the end of September 2010 stood at 86.55 billion US dollars, equivalent to 6.5 months of imports and servicing of official external debt.

The rupiah has appreciated further in keeping with the still sizeable current account surplus, heavy foreign capital inflows and prudently managed risks.  Rupiah gains have been bolstered by positive global sentiment and growing strength of domestic fundamentals.  Measured in comparison to Q2/2010, the rupiah appreciated by an average of 1.2% (qtq) to Rp 9,001 to the US dollar. The third quarter appreciation was accompanied by reduced volatility, down from 0.5% in Q2/2010 to 0.2% in Q3/2010. At end-Q3/2010, the rupiah closed at Rp 8,924 per US dollar, up 1.2% (ptp) from Q2/2010. The stable value of the rupiah offers support for importing the necessary raw materials for domestic production, while on the other hand, the rupiah appreciation has not borne down significantly on exporters because of continued strong international demand.

Financial market conditions showed improved stability during Q3/2010. The Indonesian government securities market and capital market saw further improvement, reflected in the gains in the Jakarta Composite Index (JCI) and lower yields on government securities. This improvement in the two markets during Q3/2010 was bolstered by improvement in the economic outlook. On the interbank money market, liquidity conditions maintained an upward trend.  Monetary policy transmission also operated smoothly during Q3/2010, as reflected in movement in the overnight interbank rate at about the level of the BI Rate, more robust credit expansion led by working capital credit and an all-time high in the JCI.

On the micro level, the national banking system is in even stronger condition. Reflecting this is the robust capital adequacy ratio (CAR) and the gross non-performing loans (NPLs) ratio at less than 5%. Improvement in banking liquidity, including liquidity on the interbank market, is matched by steady expansion in bank depositor funds. Banking intermediation has strengthened further, as evident in credit growth at end-September 2010 that reached 21.2% (yoy). During 2010, working capital credit has maintained faster expansion than consumption credit, and looking forward, credit growth will continue to be channelled into productive sectors. In response to these developments, credit growth for 2010 overall is forecasted at 22%-24%, in line with the business plans prepared by banks. Key to the credit expansion is more robust confidence among economic actors in the outlook for the economy.

On 5 October 2010, the Meeting of the Bank Indonesia Board of Governors, after considering this assessment and the outlook for the economy, decided to hold the BI Rate at 6.5% with an interest rate corridor at ±100 bps.  Key to this decision was the consideration that the 6.5% BI Rate level remains consistent with achievement of the medium-term inflation target and is regarded conducive to safeguarding financial stability and promoting the banking intermediation function in support of adequate supply-side response to accelerating demand.