In the Board of Governors' Meeting convened on 12 April 2011, Bank Indonesia decided to hold the BI Rate at 6.75%. This decision does not alter the tight bias in the Bank Indonesia monetary policy stance aimed at curbing the persistently high level of inflationary pressure in tandem with Government efforts to ease inflationary pressure from volatile foods. In the opinion of the Board of Governors, rupiah appreciation has worked effectively in mitigating pressure from imported inflation driven by rising prices for internationally-traded commodities. Furthermore, to minimise negative impact from short-term capital inflows on monetary and financial system stability, the Board of Governors also decided to replace the one-month holding period for Bank Indonesia Certificates (SBIs) with a six-month holding period, effective from 13 May 2011. Looking forward, Bank Indonesia sees available headroom for adjustment in the BI Rate level to curb any further rise in inflationary pressure. Bank Indonesia is confident that this mix of monetary and macroprudential policies, with added support from strengthened policy coordination with the Government, will safeguard macro stability and keep inflation on track with the established target at 5%±1% in 2011 and 4.5%±1% in 2012.

The Board of Governors envisages further improvement in global economic recovery, as evident in the upward revision of global economic growth projections by various international agencies. This strengthening of global optimism will also bolster growth in volume of world trade with positive impact on demand for exported products, thus contributing to domestic economic growth. However, the global economic recovery remains daunted by risks and uncertainty related to the debt crisis in some European nations and potential disruption in manufacturing output in the aftermath of the earthquake in Japan. In addition, further escalation is projected in world oil and food commodity prices, generating added inflationary pressure in many advanced nations and emerging economies including Indonesia.

On the domestic front, the Board of Governors forecasts Indonesia's economic growth to mount to 6.0%-6.5% in 2011 and 6.1%-6.6% in 2012. This performance will be bolstered by greater equilibrium in the sources of growth, with investment forging ahead alongside continued solid performance in exports. In Q2/2011, the economy is forecasted to grow at a brisk 6.4%. Investment, led by FDI, is set for an expanded role in building the capacity of the economy in keeping with buoyant domestic and external demand and the upgrading of the sovereign credit rating. At the sectoral level, high growth is predicted in all economic sectors, led by transport and communications, the trade, hotels and restaurants sector and construction.

Indonesia's balance of payments is expected to post another  surplus in 2011.  The key to this surplus will be performance in the current account and the capital and financial account. Exports are forecasted to maintain vigorous growth. Foreign portfolio capital inflows are set to remain strong, while foreign direct investment (FDI) is on an upward track. In response to these developments, the international reserves position at end-March 2011 reached 105.7 billion US dollars, equivalent to 6.3 months of imports and servicing of official external debt.

The rupiah charted further appreciation during March 2011. While this can be explained by the considerable surplus in the balance of payments and positive foreign investor perceptions of the strength of Indonesia's economic fundamentals, the rupiah gains also formed part of the Bank Indonesia policy response for curbing pressure from imported inflation. By the end of March 2011, the rupiah had strengthened 3.47% (ptp) to Rp 8,708 to the US dollar. So far, rupiah appreciation has not dented Indonesia's competitiveness in terms of the exchange rate, as reflected in the sustained high growth that marks Indonesia's non-oil and gas export performance.

Regarding prices, while inflation has embarked on a downward trend, there is considerable risk of high inflationary pressure looking forward. CPI inflation in March 2011 was recorded at 6.65% (yoy) following month-on-month deflation at 0.32% (mtm) in line with correction in food stuffs inflation. Although still high, inflation in the volatile foods category has shown a downward trend in line with Government actions to strengthen national food resilience. Similarly, administered prices have experienced only moderate inflation, a trend related to the minimum price increases announced by the Government. However, core inflation is on the rise, having reached 4.45% (yoy) or 0.25% (mtm) in March 2011 as a result of secondary effects from high food prices and mounting inflation expectations. Looking forward, risks of inflationary pressure continue to loom large, stoked by rising international commodity prices, buoyant domestic demand and high inflation expectations. Bank Indonesia will closely monitor the risk of inflationary pressure and reinforce the monetary and macroprudential policy mix to keep inflation on track with the established target.

Financial system stability remained secure, accompanied by steady improvement in the banking intermediation function and prudently managed banking liquidity. The stable condition of the banking industry is marked by secure levels of capital and liquidity, with the capital adequacy ratio (CAR) at  18% and non-performing loans (NPLs) gross managed at a comfortably safe level below 5%. Improvement in banking intermediation is also reflected in rising credit growth, recorded in March 2011 at 25.1% (yoy) on the strength of expansion in all categories of lending including credit to MSMEs.