The global economic recovery is moving ahead with increasing momentum. The economies of the US, Japan and other Asian nations are showing steady improvement. The global economic recovery process is outperforming earlier forecasts. In Q1/2010, China reported 11.3% annual growth, the highest level achieved in the past 3 years. Supporting this is the latest assessment by the IMF (WEO April), which projects world economic growth in 2010 at a more robust 4.2% compared to the originally predicted 3.9%. The improved optimism for economic growth and more buoyant activity in the world economy has boosted the volume of world trade. In this regard, global commodity prices are on an upward trend, a factor that is now spurring global inflation albeit on a low scale. Even so, the global economic recovery is still daunted by risks from the debt crisis in Greece, Portugal and Spain that could trigger negative sentiment on world financial markets.

The turnaround in the global economy has also strengthened performance in the domestic economy. At home, the economy is gathering strength from more robust growth in exports and investments alongside sustained vigorous consumption. The renewed pace of global economic activity combined with mounting commodity prices has bolstered export growth. Indonesia's share of total world exports has widened in 2010 from 0.92% to 1%. Rising investment activity is reflected in movement in various investment indicators, such as imports of capital goods, imports of raw materials and cement consumption. Besides this, various regulatory improvements and the launching of government infrastructure programmes have brought a more conducive direction to the investment climate. Improving conditions in the domestic economy were also buoyed by positive developments in various economic sectors, including trade, hotels and restaurants, agriculture and the transport and communications sector. The upbeat performance in the trade sector came not only in response to rising exports and imports, but also performance in other sectors, such as agriculture and manufacturing. In similar developments, mounting economic activity and a flurry of innovations and advances in communications services have kept the transport and communications sector on a brisk growth track.

Concerning prices, inflationary pressure remains low and under control. Prices in April 2010 were influenced by non-fundamentals in the volatile foods category. However, inflationary pressure stayed remarkably low in core items and the administered prices category. Taken together, April inflation was recorded at 0.15% (mtm) or 3.91% (yoy), up from the 0.14% deflation (mtm) in March 2010. Inflation in the volatile foods category was fuelled largely by increased prices for some seasonings, such as red chilli peppers, tomatoes, shallots and garlic, as well as several vegetable varieties. These price surges are predicted to be temporary, being caused by disruptions in supply and distribution brought on by adverse weather conditions in some farming production centres. Inflationary pressure from administered prices was again low due to the absence of strategic government decisions related to prices. No significant pressure was recorded in core inflation, due to the appreciating trend in the rupiah. Added to this, inflationary pressure from externals was also minimal, due to movements in global commodity prices that despite some increases remained within modest limits. Inflationary pressure from supply-demand interaction is expected to stay low, given the adequate support of supply-side response to rising demand. In regard to expectations, inflation expectations remained subdued and in decline. The low inflation of the past several months and appreciating trend in the rupiah have maintained a healthy level of inflation expectations.

Indonesia's balance of payments is expected to chart continued solid performance, bolstered by strengthening exports. The improved performance in trading partner economies will provide added lift to Indonesia's exports. In addition to resource-based commodities, such as coal, copper, rubber and crude palm oil (CPO), Indonesia's exports have also benefited from stronger performance in manufactured products. Further boost to exports came from movements in commodity prices. The Indonesian export price index (IHKEI) has maintained an upward trend since Q2/2009. Similarly, imports have also mounted in response to acceleration in domestic and export demand. Regarding the capital and financial account, positive perceptions of the Indonesian economy have stimulated heavy inflows of foreign portfolio capital into Indonesia. Market jitters over the fiscal crisis in Greece prompted global investors to shift funds to Asia, where economic recovery is advancing at a faster rate. Inflows of foreign direct investment (FDI) have also benefited from the upbeat performance of the domestic economy and faster than expected recovery in the global economy. Optimism for further improvement in the domestic economy will also lead to increased equity and reinvested earnings, particularly in the non-oil and gas sector. In response to these developments, international reserves on 30 April 2010 stood at 78.6 billion US dollars, equivalent to 6.2 months of imports and servicing of official external debt.

The solid performance in the balance of payments has contributed to the strengthening of the rupiah. The rupiah has maintained an upward trend in response to the rising wave of capital inflows into Asia. The high returns on Asian investments offer particular incentive for foreign investors to channel their funds to Asian financial markets, including Indonesia. On the domestic front, investor perceptions were reassured by the secure condition of economic fundamentals, Favourable investor perceptions were reflected in stable indicators for investment risk in Indonesia, which have sustained keen foreign investor interest in Indonesia. During April, the rupiah recorded 1.5% average appreciation to Rp 9,027 to the US dollar before closing the month at Rp 9,012 to the US dollar, up 0.87% from the previous month's close. Accompanying the strengthening trend in the rupiah was subdued volatility. Volatility in the rupiah fell to 0.23% in April 2010 from 0.45% one month earlier.

The upbeat condition of the domestic and global economy has also brought improvement to the financial sector. Plentiful liquidity in the banking system helped bring down the weighted average overnight rate towards the lower end of the interest rate corridor. At the same time, the high rate of foreign capital inflows that boosted performance on the domestic financial market, as reflected in the soaring JSX Composite index and lower yields on Indonesian government securities. At end-April, the JSX Composite Index closed at 2,971, ahead of the March 2010 closing position of 2,777. Key to this performance is mounting investor optimism over the improving economic performance of Indonesia, in addition to subdued inflation. In April 2010, daily volume of share trading reached Rp 5.3 trillion, up from the March 2010 level of Rp 4.7 trillion per day. The bullish performance of the JSX Composite as of April 2010 placed Indonesia's stock exchange as the third best performing market in Asia after Vietnam and Singapore. On the government securities market, investors again displayed optimism for the future for the Indonesian economy, visible in lower yield on government securities across various tenors.

At the micro level, conditions in the national banking system remain stable. Reflecting this is the still comfortable level of the capital adequacy ratio (CAR) at 19.1% in March 2010. Similarly, the gross non-performing loans (NPLs) ratio held below 3.8% with the net NPLs ratio at 1%. In March 2010, depositor funds registered 11.9% growth (yoy), up from growth in the preceding month at 9.3% (yoy).

On 5 May 2010, the Board of Governors' Meeting at Bank Indonesia resolved to hold the BI Rate at 6.5% with an interest rate corridor as stated earlier. In the assessment of the Bank Indonesia Board of Governors, the 6.50% level in the BI Rate remains consistent with the 5%±1% inflation target for 2010 and is also conducive to the economic recovery process and operation of banking intermediation.