The world economic outlook is expected to perform better, although overshadowed by rising inflationary pressures as world oil and food prices continue to pick up. World economic growth is forecasted to surpass earlier projections, buoyed by the improved recovery in advanced economies, while growth in the emerging markets keeps forging ahead. In keeping with these developments, world commodity prices are on an upward trend marked by soaring oil prices. As a result, inflationary pressure is building up in both emerging markets and advanced economies, spurred by the soaring trend in food and energy prices. Geopolitical developments in the Middle East have not only influenced oil prices, but also put pressure on global financial markets. Added downward pressure on global financial markets has come from the decision by the People's Bank of China to launch further monetary tightening. Monetary tightening in response to growing inflationary pressures, which previously took place in emerging markets, was also observed in; advanced countries.

The improving outlook in the global economy has boosted the domestic economy, mainly through recent growth in exports. The domestic economy is predicted to chart brisk growth in Q1/2011, despite some slowing from the previous quarter. The projected 6.4% growth in Q1/2011 is bolstered mainly by high levels of exports growth, while household consumption and investment will keep growing at positive levels albeit lower than previous quarter. Exports performance remains strong in line with the global economic recovery. Imports also continue to pick up, driven by vibrant domestic demand and strong external demand. Household consumption growth has somewhat tapered off from the effect of declining real incomes, particularly in low and middle income households. The modest progress in infrastructure projects has had a dampening effect on investment activity. From external side, the balance of payments has posted another considerable surplus. The capital and financial account is forecasted to remain in surplus amid outflows in the early quarter triggered by rising inflationary pressure. Contributing to this surplus is the expected increase in FDI, while portfolio inflows are expected to remain strong. At the same time, the current account is expected to post another surplus, a development bolstered mainly by high commodity prices. Bolstered by solid external developments, international reserves position on 28 February 2011 reached 99.6 billion US dollars, equivalent to 6.1 months of imports and servicing of official debt. On 3 March 2011, the position rose to 101.8 billion US dollars, equivalent to 6.2 months of imports and servicing of official external debt.

Following a brief pause in January 2011, the rupiah resumed an appreciating trend in February. This was driven in part by renewed inflows of capital influenced by positive foreign investor perceptions on the strength of Indonesia's economic fundamentals. Nevertheless, the rupiah gains also represented a positive response to the BI Rate increase and the Bank Indonesia policy to provide room for rupiah appreciation under its strong commitment to tame inflation. During February 2011, the rupiah strengthened 2.5% (ptp) to close the month at Rp 8,818 to the US dollar. Thus far, the rupiah appreciation has not impacted Indonesia's competitiveness, given the appreciation trend across the region during this period with some currencies charting higher appreciation.

CPI inflation eased slightly in February 2011, despite the risk of high inflationary pressure going forward. CPI inflation in February 2011 came to 0.13% (mtm) or 6.84% (yoy), down from one month earlier. Price corrections for rice and chilli peppers following government policy to improve supply contributed to 0.48% (mtm) deflation in the volatile foods category. Alongside this, administered prices were again marked by modest inflationary pressure with increases at only 0.32% (mtm) or 5.34% (yoy). Nevertheless, Bank Indonesia is keeping a close watch on a renewed increase in core inflation, now recorded at 0.31% (mtm) or 4.36% (yoy), particularly in regard to the impact of high volatile foods inflation and rising international commodity prices. Indications of inflation expectations
on financial markets began to ease, although still high, in response to the increase in the BI Rate, while inflation expectations among producers, traders and consumers have been largely unaffected. For this reason, Bank Indonesia will take further monetary and macroprudential policy, including measures to contain the effects of higher imported inflation through rupiah appreciation.

Financial system stability was maintained alongside steady improvement in the banking intermediation function and contained banking liquidity. The stable condition of the banking industry was reflected in prudently managed capital and liquidity, marked by a high capital adequacy ratio (CAR) and favorable ratio for gross non-performing loans (NPLs) at below 5%. Further improvement in banking intermediation was also evident in more robust credit growth, recorded at 24.6% (yoy) in January 2011 as a result of expansion in all credit categories including credit to MSMEs. No indicators suggest that the BI Rate hike in February 2011 was followed by rising bank interest rates. In related developments, the prescribed levels of LDR-based and foreign currency statutory reserves started from March 1, 2011, were complied by the banks.

Domestic financial market performance resumed gains following a downturn in early 2011. The upturn in the financial market is reflected, among others, in the renewed recovery in stock market performance and stable Indonesian government securities. On the money market, liquidity narrowed slightly, came from the contraction of government budget and the exchange rate stabilisation policy. In regard to monetary policy transmission, bank interest rates have not fully responded to the BI Rate increase in February 2011. Neither has the monetary policy signal produced a response in the overnight interbank rate. However, monetary policy transmission is predicted to proceed further in view of the lag effect of monetary policy. In addition, Bank Indonesia»s measures to improve monetary management will also bolster monetary policy transmission.

In the Board of Governors' Meeting convened on 4 March 2011, Bank Indonesia decided for the time being to hold the BI Rate at 6.75%. This decision does not alter the tight bias in the Bank Indonesia monetary policy stance aimed at curbing the high level of inflation. Bank Indonesia keeps a close watch on future developments of inflation and will respond with carefully timed and measured adjustments in the BI Rate. Measures to curb imported inflation from escalating international commodity prices have been reinforced by providing added room for rupiah appreciation in line with improving global economic fundamentals. Other actions will strengthen liquidity management through a combination of macroprudential polices and monetary operations while allowing for reasonable banking liquidity needs. Among these are the new LDR-based and foreign currency statutory reserve requirements, effective from 1 March 2011. With this monetary and macroprudential policy mix supported by a robust government commitment to lower high food commodity prices, as demonstrated in coordination of inflation control at the central government and regional levels, Bank Indonesia is confident that CPI inflation can be curbed in line with the target of 5% ± 1% for 2011 and 4.5% ± 1% for 2012.