The global economic recovery under way is feared could stall due to slowing economic activity in the US, China and Japan. The US economic slowdown is explained primarily by stubbornly high unemployment that has depressed household consumption. The weak purchasing power of households has led to slowing activity in the manufacturing sector. In Japan, the economic slowdown has been caused mainly by deteriorating export performance, a result of a strong yen that has reached a 15-year high against the US dollar. At the same time, government action to tighten lending has slowed investment and consumption in China. This policy decision is slowing the pace of China's economy, although growth remains at a buoyant level.

The Indonesian economy is steadily improving, but not in all areas.  This is indicated by the sizeable role of household consumption in contrast to investment, which despite growth is not at optimal levels. In analysis by sector, non-tradable sectors are expanding at a brisk pace in contrast to the limited growth in tradable sectors and especially manufacturing. Various constraints to investment have contributed to limited capacity for economic growth.  Under these conditions, efforts to accelerate demand side expansion must be adjusted to the supply side capacity for response.

CPI inflation in August 2010 was marked by rising pressure from fundamentals, while pressure eased from non-fundamentals and particularly volatile foods. Pressure in core inflation during August 2010 came mainly from a surge in educational expenses in the seasonal trend marking the beginning of the new academic year, as well as increases in air fares. Added to this, price increases in the processed foods category triggered by high volatile foods inflation and the seasonal rise in demand in advance of religious festivities added to the pressure in the core inflation category. On the external side, the impact of imported inflation from escalating global commodity prices and inflation in trading partners has not generated significant upward pressure on core inflation, due to the appreciating trend in the rupiah. Regarding non-fundamentals, inflationary pressure during August 2010 was fuelled by increased electricity billing rates for household consumers. However, volatile foods inflation eased in line with the harvest of some seasonings and vegetable commodities. Amid these developments, CPI inflation in August 2010 was recorded at 0.76% (mtm), down from the preceding period. However, in the annual measure, inflationary pressure is up, having mounted from 6.22% (yoy) in July 2010 to 6.44% (yoy).

Indonesia’s balance of payments has again posted an estimated surplus. Key to this is the performance of the capital and financial account bolstered by a sharp rise in capital inflows for portfolio investments. In the current account, however, imports are growing at a brisk pace. The rise in imports has come in response to more vigorous domestic economic activity, particularly in preparation for the religious festive season. In the outcome of these developments, international reserves at 31 August 23010 reached USD81.3 billion, equivalent to 6.1 months of imports and servicing of official debt.

During August 2010, the rupiah maintained an appreciating trend, bolstered by positive perceptions of the economy and high returns on rupiah instruments. The strength of this attraction prompted renewed increases in capital inflows with significant funds pouring into instruments on the financial market. During the month, the rupiah exchange rate averaged Rp 8,972 to the USD, a gain of 0.78% (mtm). At end-August 2010, the rupiah closed at Rp 9,035 to the US dollar, having weakened 0.95% (point to point) from end-July 2010. The strengthening in the rupiah was accompanies by slightly increased volatility. During August 2010, volatility in the rupiah averaged 0.28%, up from 0.19% in the previous month.

Indonesia's financial market charted improved performance marked by gains in the JCI and lower yield on government securities across all tenors. One key factor was the high volume of capital inflows. In the area of monetary policy transmission, bank lending rates continued to ease. Bank interest rates for funds and credit moved yet lower, although at a slower pace and accompanied by a narrower spread. In the credit channel, credit expansion is on the rise, bolstered mainly by consumption credit even in spite of the increased contributions from investment credit and working capital credit. Liquidity conditions in the economy have maintained an improving trend in line with the rise in economic activity.

Financial system stability, like before, is well under control, bolstered by the robust condition of the banking sector in mitigating risks and improvement in the banking intermediation function.  This is indicated, among others, by the high capital adequacy ratio (CAR) at 16.6% and the safe level of non-performing loans (NPLs) gross at below 5.0%. Improvement in the banking intermediation function is reflected in more robust credit expansion at 20.3% (yoy) in August 2010. 
In the Board of Governors' Meeting convened on 3 September 2010, Bank Indonesia decided to keep the BI Rate at 6.50%. However, in view of the potential for future inflationary pressure and the considerable excess liquidity in the banking system, the Board of Governors emphasises the importance of raising the Primary Statutory Reserve Requirement from 5% to 8% of rupiah depositor funds. The additional 3% held in Primary Statutory Reserves will be remunerated at 2.50% p.a. This policy combination is considered adequate to safeguard monetary stability and financial system stability amid the present high rate of capital inflows. Similarly, to promote the banking intermediation function, the Board of Governors has also imposed a statutory reserve requirement based on the LDR (loan to deposit ratio) as a means of ensuring credit growth firmly based on prudential banking principles. Under this requirement, the lower limit of the LDR is 78% and the upper limit 100%. A bank with an LDR outside this range will be subject to a disincentive based on variance in the LDR from the targeted range. If the LDR is higher than the target but the bank maintains adequate capital, it will receive an incentive. The new statutory reserves policy will be phased in with the primary statutory reserve requirement launched on 1 November 210 and the LDR statutory reserve requirement effective from 1 March 2011.