?In the Board of Governors' Meeting convened on 12 November 2013, Bank Indonesia decided to raise the BI Rate by 25 bps to 7.50%, while the Lending Facility and Deposit Facility rates were similarly increased to 7.50% and 5.75%. This policy has been pursued in view of the sizeable deficit in the current account against a background of high risks of global uncertainty that continue unabated. Accordingly, this decision was taken to ensure a reduction in the current account deficit to a healthier level and continued low inflation on track with the 4.5±1% target in 2014 in support of sustainable economic growth. Looking forward, Bank Indonesia is keeping close watch on a number of risks in the global and national economy and intends to optimise the monetary and macroprudential policy mix. Bank Indonesia will also continue to forge closer coordination with the Government to control inflation and manage the current account deficit, including policy coordination for structural improvement of the economy.

Global economic developments showed some improvement in October 2013, although still daunted by heightened risks of uncertainty. The positive developments in the global economy were spurred mainly by positive sentiment on global financial markets over the postponed deliberations of the US debt ceiling and delay in "tapering off" by the Fed. At the same time, the outlook for global economic growth is on track with earlier predictions. Despite this, Bank Indonesia is keenly aware that global economic developments remain shrouded in uncertainty. A shift is underway in composition of world growth, with economies slowing in emerging markets and picking up in the developed world. In addition, the high point of the world commodity price cycle is predicted to end, which may hamper the drive for recovery in the Indonesian economy. Both trends will affect Indonesia's external economic performance.

Indonesia underwent a period of slowing economic growth in Q3/2013, in line with earlier forecasts. During the quarter, the Indonesian economy grew by 5.6% (yoy), down from the Q2/2013 level of 5.8% (yoy). Economic slowdown was recorded mainly in investment due to falling construction investment and the low growth rate in non-construction investment. Exports showed improvement in real terms, albeit accompanied by rising total exports. In other developments, consumption was marked by increases in both household consumption and government consumption. In the opinion of Bank Indonesia, the economic slowdown is partly explained by the influence of stabilisation policies launched by the Government and Bank Indonesia to set the economy on a healthier and more balanced course. In view of developments as far as the third quarter, Bank Indonesia again predicts Indonesia's economic growth in 2013 to come within the range of earlier projections at 5.5%-5.9%, with growth set to rise to 5.8%-6.2% in 2014.

On the external side, Indonesia's balance of payments sustained further pressure from deficits in Q3/2013. The current account deficit is expected to fall to US$8.4 billion for Q3/2013, compared to almost US$10.0 billion one quarter earlier. Improvement is most visible in the non-oil and gas commodity trade surplus (fob) that resulted from slackening non-oil and gas imports in keeping with the slowing pace of domestic demand. In other developments, the services account and income account also posted reduced deficits. However, oil and gas trade deficit mounted higher due to shrinking domestic production and persistently high imports of oil and gas for domestic consumption. Meanwhile, the capital and financial account posted a reduced surplus in response to a drop in portfolio capital inflows caused by the lingering high uncertainty on global financial markets. Nevertheless, improvement was recorded in foreign direct investment (FDI). Taken together, Indonesia's international reserves reached US$97.0 billion at end-October 2013, having been strengthened by US$1.3 billion from the end-September 2013 position of US$95.7 billion. At this level, the international reserves position is equivalent to 5.5 months of imports or equivalent to 5.3 months of imports and servicing of official external debt. Bank Indonesia regards this as a comfortably safe level that supports external sector resilience, exceeding the international standard for adequacy.

During October 2013, the rupiah remained largely stable, moving in tandem with fundamentals. Measured point-to-point, the rupiah gained 2.73% (mtm) to close at Rp 11,273 to the US dollar, but in average terms the rupiah weakened 0.14% (mtm) to Rp 11,343 to the US dollar. Influencing this movement were the reasonably buoyant global financial market conditions in October 2013 combined with a fall in domestic inflation expectations that in turn attracted capital inflows into domestic financial market instruments, led by Bank Indonesia Certificates (SBIs) and Indonesian government bonds. The stable exchange rate is also attributable to subdued demand for non-oil and gas imports in keeping with more modest economic growth. Looking forward, Bank Indonesia will continue to manage stability in the rupiah in line with the condition of fundamentals.

Easing of inflationary pressure continued into October 2013. CPI inflation in October 2013 was recorded at 0.09% (mtm) or 8.32% (yoy), reinforcing indications that inflation has returned to the normal monthly trend. Inflationary pressure eased largely from developments in the foodstuffs category, while administered prices inflation and core inflation were generally stable. The stable level of core inflation at 4.37% (yoy) is explained in part by reduced external pressures, with global food prices on a downward trend. The impact of exchange rate depreciation on inflation was also quite low. With inflationary pressure down, overall inflation for 2013 is predicted to come slightly below 9.0% and subsequently drop to the 4.5±1% target range in 2014.

Financial system stability has held firm, bolstered by the solid resilience of the banking industry. During September 2013, the capital adequacy ratio (CAR) held steady at a robust 18.0%, well above the 8% regulatory minimum, while non-performing loans (NPLs) were kept comfortably low at 1.86%. Credit expansion in September 2013 reached 23.1% (yoy), up from the August 2013 growth of 22.2% (yoy). However, the rise in credit expansion is explained more by the revaluation effect from weakening in the rupiah exchange rate. When calculated with a fixed exchange rate, credit growth showed a downward trend, slipping from 20.2% (yoy) in August 2013 to 19.9% (yoy) in September 2013. Bank Indonesia sees this slowing trend in credit expansion as consistent with the effect of the cooling domestic economy and predicts credit growth in the 18%-20% range for 2013 overall.