Global economic conditions have improved further despite risks from uncertainties in the outlook for US economic recovery and the economic slowdown in China. The ongoing improvement in global growth is supported by vibrant growth in emerging markets and renewed improvement in the economies of Europe. Key to the turnaround in the economic fortunes of Europe are rising manufactured exports and better than predicted results from European bank stress test, which relieved pressures bearing down on global financial markets. Reflecting this is more robust performance on global stock markets and steady improvement in risk perceptions. Despite this, global economic recovery remains overshadowed by uncertainties from developments in some US economic indicators in recent months that point to slowing economic expansion. US consumption continues to be dogged by a credit crunch and rising unemployment. US manufacturing activity is also slackening in response to weakened domestic consumption. Besides this, the global economic recovery faces risks from China. China's economy is charting more modest growth as a result of government policy actions to avoid overheating.

The steady improvement in global economic conditions has had a positive effect on the domestic economy. The present recovery in the global economy is providing a boost to exports, particularly for manufactured goods. Furthermore, comparatively stable public purchasing power has kept domestic demand at buoyant levels. Growing exports and rising domestic demand have met with positive response in more robust investment. Positive developments are especially visible in non-construction investment, reflected in higher import growth for capital goods and raw materials and more vigorous commercial vehicle sales. The stronger investment growth is also supported by a conducive domestic investment climate, among others in response to changes in various investment regulations. Performance is up in almost all economic sectors in line with the improvement in global and domestic economic conditions. Key sectors reporting strong performance are manufacturing, the trade, hotels and restaurants sector, construction and the transport and communications sector.

Concerning prices, inflationary pressure mounted significantly in July 2010 in response to non-fundamentals, led by volatile foods. During July 2010, inflation in the consumer price index (CPI) reached 1.57% (mtm) or 6.22% (yoy), up from the previous month's levels of 0.97% (mtm) or 5.05% (yoy) due to uncertain seasonal conditions and disrupted production and distribution related to heavy rains. This led to significant price increases for food commodities, most importantly rice and miscellaneous seasonings due to their susceptibility to changing weather conditions. Price increases recorded in July 2010 were considerably greater than the historical averages in the foodstuffs category. In the core inflation category, inflation was more subdued due to the adequate supply-side response to rising demand and the appreciating trend in the exchange rate. Therefore, most of the factors driving inflation are seasonal, requiring action to safeguard against increased expectations of future inflation. In view of price movements as of July 2010 and the rising consumption related to the seasonal religious festivities, CPI inflation for 2010 overall is forecasted to reach the upper limit of the Bank Indonesia inflation target.

The estimated performance of the balance of payments remains solid. Rising domestic economic activity is expected to stimulate import growth leading to a modest reduction in the current account surplus. Imports are rising in both the oil and natural gas sector and non-oil and gas sector in line with the increased absorption in the domestic economy with the approach of the religious festive season. Nevertheless, the import growth is adequately offset by brisk growth in exports fuelled by conducive conditions in the global economy and the sustained high level of commodity prices. Estimates for the capital and financial account again point to a surplus spurred largely by mounting portfolio capital inflows in line with positive investor perceptions of the economic outlook for Indonesia. Following these developments, the international reserves position at 30 July 2010 reached USD78.8 billion, equivalent to 6.03 months of imports and servicing of official external debt.

Indonesia's solid economic fundamentals and conducive conditions on global financial markets have bolstered the rupiah. During July, the average exchange rate for the rupiah appreciated 1.07% to Rp 9,042 to the US dollar. The appreciation in the rupiah during July 2010 was accompanied by reduced volatility. In July 2010, volatility in the rupiah eased to 0.19% from 0.51% in the preceding month. The stable movement in the rupiah is attributable to relative stability in global economic conditions, adequate supply and demand for foreign currency on the domestic market and the implementation of policies for managing capital flows that include the SBI one-month holding period introduced on 7 July 2010.

Financial markets have maintained stable performance. Reflecting this is movement in the overnight interbank rate, which continued to hover above the BI Rate level, faster M1 growth in response to mounting economic activity and upbeat developments on the stock market and government securities market. Stable macroeconomic conditions and the downward trend in external risk factors boosted prices for assets, including the composite share price index (JCI). The JCI gains during July 2010 came in response to policy decisions concerning the BI Rate and the Policy Package for Enhanced Monetary Management and Financial Market Expansion, as well as the upgrading of Indonesia's sovereign credit rating outlook. These developments boosted the stock index by 5.3% to a new high of 3,096.8 on 29 July 2010 before closing the month at 3,069.68. The upbeat performance in the JCI was also matched by gains on the government securities market. Key factors in the performance of government securities included not only the stable exchange rate, rating upgrade and positive outlook for the economy, but also limited fiscal risk and prudent fiscal sustainability. In regard to monetary policy, the upbeat performance in government securities also came in response to the Bank Indonesia decision to hold the BI Rate at 6.5% and the introduction of the one-month SBI holding period.

Financial system stability remains strong, bolstered by the robust condition of the banking sector. The stable condition of the financial sector is supported by the strength of the banking system in addressing various risks, as well as improvement in the bank intermediation function. Indications of this include the high capital adequacy ratio (CAR) for the banking system, currently at 17.4 %, and subdued level of non-performing loans (NPLs) gross at below 5.0%. Improvement in banking intermediation is reflected in the rate of credit expansion at end-July 2010, recorded at 19.6% (yoy). This is consistent with the mounting confidence of economic actors in the improving economic outlook. Looking forward, Bank Indonesia will keep a close watch on this bank lending growth to keep it within the lending range envisaged in the Bank Business Plans, particularly regarding credit for productive purposes, and is commensurate with supply-side growth in the economy. The purpose of these measures is to ensure that demand-side increase will be adequately offset on the supply-side and thus not generate excessive inflationary pressure.

In the Board of Governors' Meeting convened on 4 August 2010, Bank Indonesia decided to keep the BI Rate at 6.5%. This decision was taken after a comprehensive evaluation of the latest developments and outlook for the economy, which point to steady overall improvement. Despite this, the recent inflationary surge is a matter of special concern. Bank Indonesia will pursue the necessary monetary and banking policy actions to ensure that future inflation remains on track with the established target at 5%±1% for 2010 and 2011. The Board of Governors considers the current 6.5% BI Rate adequate to safeguard future inflation expectations while closely monitoring the recent rise in inflation. In the near future, Bank Indonesia will respond with measures to tighten liquidity management without disruption to the bank intermediation function, implemented through changes in the statutory reserve requirement.