The increasing outlook in the world economy has given added impetus to domestic economic performance. World economic growth is forecasted to surpass earlier projections, buoyed by the improved recovery in advanced economies, while growth forges ahead in the emerging markets of the developing world. This trend reinforces confidence that the Indonesian economy will chart 6% growth for 2010 and improve further so that by end-2011, growth is forecasted to reach 6.0%-6.5%. Growth in Q1/2011 is predicted to reach 6.4%, bolstered by robust domestic demand and external-side improvements. Export performance remains strong in line with the global economic recovery. Imports are also rising, particularly for capital goods needed to support capacity expansion in the economy. Accordingly, the current account in Q1/2011 is forecasted to post a large surplus. A large surplus is also predicted for the capital and financial account, mainly from heavy capital inflows for direct investment (FDI). At the same time, foreign portfolio investment in Indonesian government securities, stocks and Bank Indonesia Certificates (SBIs), hit by capital outflows in the second and third weeks of January due to negative sentiment from the risks of inflationary pressure and US dollar appreciation, recovered to normal by the fourth week of the month. Taken together, the Indonesia balance of payments is forecasted to chart a respectable surplus in Q1/2011. International reserves at 31 January 2011 were recorded at 95.3 billion US dollars, equivalent to 6.3 months of imports and servicing of official external debt.

The rupiah exchange rate came under  pressure from capital outflows. The rupiah weakened while charting increased volatility, a development sparked among others by market jitters over rising domestic inflationary pressure. During January 2011, the rupiah exchange rate fell by an average 0.1% to Rp 9,034 to the US dollar. Bank Indonesia is confident that the capital outflows and rupiah depreciation are more of a temporary  pressure in view of the strength of Indonesia's economic fundamentals as attested by the decision by the Moody's rating agency to boost Indonesia's sovereign credit rating to Ba1 with outlook stable.  Furthermore, Bank Indonesia policies aimed at exchange rate stabilisation have helped to restore the stability of the rupiah.

Inflation expectations have begun to climb. CPI inflation in January 2011 reached 0.89% (mtm) or 7.02% (yoy). The high rate of inflation is explained primarily by strong volatile foods inflation running at 18.25% (yoy) as a result of further crop losses and disruptions in distribution of rice and seasonings. However, administered prices charted moderate inflation at 5.21% (yoy), while core inflation was relatively subdued at a mild 4.18% (yoy). Despite this, inflation expectations have begun to climb as reflected in various inflation expectation indicators, such as the consumer expectations survey, producer surveys and prices for financial assets. While triggered by the steep increases in volatile food prices, the surge in inflation expectations has also been prompted by rising global commodity prices and the Government plan to reduce the fuel subsidy.  Bank Indonesia believes that the rising inflation expectations call for an appropriate response to avert future inflationary pressures.

Performance on domestic financial markets also came under pressure from foreign investor jitters over mounting inflation. Pressure bore down on the money and stock markets and the government securities market. The stock market underwent significant correction with the Jakarta Composite Index (JCI) tumbling about 7.9%. However, similar downturns were evident in other countries in the region, including China, India and the Philippines.  This bearish condition also spilled over into the government securities, as indicated by significantly increased yields. In regard to monetary policy transmission, bank interest rates eased further although at a more limited rate with a narrowing spread. At the same time, the overnight interbank rate began to climb, edging closer to the BI Rate level. This was also commensurate with the policy instrument optimisation undertaken to improve monetary policy effectiveness. 

Financial system stability remained secure alongside steady improvement in the banking intermediation function. The solid condition of the banking industry is reflected in the high capital adequacy ratio (CAR) and subdued non-performing loans (NPLs) gross at below 5%. Further improvement in banking intermediation is also reflected in progressively improving credit growth, recorded in 2010 at 22.8% (yoy) on the strength of expansion in all lending categories including credit to MSMEs.

In the Board of Governor’s Meeting convened on 4 February 2011, Bank Indonesia decided to increase the BI Rate by 25 basis points (bps) or 0.25% to 6.75%, based on the latest assessment and outlook for the economy. This decision represents an anticipatory measure to curb the renewed surge in expectations of future inflation. The rise in inflation expectations has been triggered primarily by further steep increases in volatile food prices, in addition to escalating prices for globally-traded commodities, including oil, and Government policy planning for strategic commodities. Bank Indonesia will keep a close watch on future inflation developments and reinforce the rupiah exchange rate policy in line with measures to subdue future inflationary pressures in addition to the macroprudential policies introduced in 2010. With this monetary and macroprudential policy mix and Government actions to bring down high food commodity prices, inflation is predicted to stay on course for the target of 5% ±1% for 2011 and 4.5% ±1% for 2012.