The Board of Governors view that the performance of domestic economy continues to strengthen. The economic growth in Q2/2011 is satisfactory, i.e. as forecasted at 6.5%, and is forecasted to accelerate. The economy is forecasted to grow at 6.6% in Q3/2011 and troughout 2011. This stronger growth performance is bolstered by a remained solid export performance, strong household consumption and investment due to higher demand and the realization of Government’s capital expenditure. By economic sector, the growth are projected to be led by the trade, hotels and restaurant sector; transportation and communication sector; and manufacturing sector.

Indonesia’s balance of payments in Q3/2011 is forecasted to remain posting a surplus albeit lower than the surplus in Q2/2011. Accelerating domestic economic activities are projected to boost imports, particularly oil and gas, that potentially put pressures on current account. Nevertheless, the pressures on current account can be compensated by a surplus in capital and financial account due to the continuing large capital inflows. In line with the development in the balance of payments, international reserves at the end of July, 2011 reached USD 122.7 billion, or equivalent to 7.0 months of imports and external debt services of the Government.

The rupiah exchange rate is projected to remain stable with a tendency to moderately appreciate. In July 2011, the Rupiah appreciated by 0.95% (ptp) to Rp 8,496 per USD with lower volatility. The movements of the Rupiah in July 2011 were also influenced by high corporate demand for foreign exchange due to their larger import payments. However, the increase in the foreign exchange demand can still be offset by foreign exchange supply as large capital inflows continues.

Inflation pressure has been under control, as reflected by inflation in July that was still in line with its seasonality. The CPI inflation in July 2011 was recorded at 0.67% (qtq) so that it annually decelerated to 4.61% (yoy). The inflation in July was relatively normal compared with its historical pattern. Going forward, inflationary pressure is mainly emanating from the increase in household consumption during Ramadhan and Eid holidays. Nevertheless, Government policies on securing supply of foods, including through imports, is predicted to mitigate volatility of the prices further so that inflation will be under control.

On the other hand, banking developments remained stable, accompanied by a steady improvement in banking intermediation. The stable condition of the banking industry is marked by secure level of capital, with capital adequacy ratio (CAR) above the minimum level at 8% and non-performing loans (NPLs) gross managed at a comfortable level below 5%. Meanwhile, credit disbursement to finance economic activities continues, reflected in the rising credit growth that reached 23.6% (yoy) in July 2011. Bank Indonesia will sustain efforts to optimize the intermediation function of the banking sector in bolstering national economic expansion while continuously maintaining the stability of the overall banking system. 