The Indonesian economy gained added momentum during Q2/2010. Optimism was buoyed by investment performance and accelerated export growth in keeping with the recovery in the global economy. Conditions in the economy, marked by growing optimism, support a more upbeat outlook compared to earlier forecasts. In 2010, Indonesia's economic growth is heading for the upper limit of the 5.5%-6.0% range and in 2011 is predicted to reach 6.0%-6.5%. In regard to prices, inflationary pressure mounted higher in Q2/2010 in response to developments in volatile food items, led by miscellaneous seasonings and rice. In contrast, administered prices and core inflation accounted for a minimum contribution to price movements during Q2/2010. Accordingly, for the year as a whole, CPI inflation will remain within the 5%±1% inflation targeting range.

The global economic recovery charted further progress despite pressures on global financial markets and concerns over the sustainability of recovery in Europe. In estimates for Q2/2010, global recovery moved at a more moderate pace compared to Q1/2010. Nevertheless, these developments have reinforced optimism in the process for global recovery with added support from improving conditions in advanced economies, led by the US and Japan, and some Asian countries. In Asia, economic growth gathered pace except in China, where activity slowed somewhat due to government policy actions in response to signs of overheating. Pressure from the European crisis bore down on global financial markets throughout Q2/2010, as reflected in plunging stock indices worldwide and sharp increases in CDS and yield spreads for the PIIGS nations (Portugal, Italy, Ireland, Greece and Spain). In Asia, flight to quality was indicated by net selling by foreign investors on stock markets, weakening in regional currencies and increased CDS on sovereign debt. So far, the European crisis has taken its toll more on global financial markets and has not significantly affected the overall outlook for global economic recovery. Various measures pursued by the crisis-hit nations in Europe, such as austerity programmes and aid from the EU and IMF, have quelled the turmoil that beset global financial markets during Q2/2010.

Domestic economic performance in Q2/2010 is estimated ahead of earlier projections. During Q2/2010, the domestic economy grew by an estimated 6.0%, surpassing the original projection at 5.7%. Key to this optimism is renewed momentum in investment growth. In Q2/2010, investment growth reached an estimated 10% (yoy) in response to strengthening domestic and external demand. The more favourable investment climate also received a boost from the upgrading of Indonesia's sovereign credit rating in keeping with improvement in economic fundamentals. In analysis by sector, economy performance in 2010 is fuelled by the trade, hotels and restaurants sector and transport and communications. The accelerated pace of the domestic economy also requires support primarily in relation to more rapid implementation of infrastructure programmes.

Stronger economic growth was also reflected in more vigorous growth in regional economies. Regional economic performance was bolstered mainly by the economies in Jakarta, Western Java, Eastern Java and Sulawesi, the Moluccan islands and Papua. The improving economic performance in the regions is supported mainly by stronger consumption, investment and exports. The brisk pace of household consumption growth in these regions is evident in the increased growth in consumption lending, sustained high growth in retail sales and stable farmer terms of trade in some areas.  In addition, the elections for regional heads of government during Q2/2010 have also boosted consumption in the regions. Investment is growing mainly in the area of construction. Vibrant activity in construction investment is under way in Sumatra, Jakarta and Java, Bali and Nusa Tenggara. The construction investment in these regions mainly involves property developments for commercial and residential use. Export growth continues at a brisk pace for mining commodities from Kalimantan, Sulawesi, the Moluccan island, Papua and Sumatra, and for manufactured products from Jakarta, Bali and Nusa Tenggara.

In regard to prices, inflationary pressure gathered pace in Q2/2010 due to developments in non-fundamentals. Increased prices for seasonings and rice throughout the second quarter generated significant upward pressure on CPI inflation. In June 2010, CPI inflation was recorded at 0.97% (mtm), up from earlier months marked by inflation at 0.15% in May and -0.14% in April 2010. Taken together, CPI inflation in Q2/2010 reached 1.41% (qtq) or 5.05% (yoy), up significantly from 0.99% (yoy) and 3.43% (yoy) in the preceding quarter. The strong inflation in foodstuff commodities is explained by supply constraints caused by problems in production and distribution following heavy rains in some areas. In contrast, developments in the administered prices category had little effect on CPI inflation. On the fundamentals side, pressure from core inflation remains low with support from subdued inflation expectations, minimum pressure from externals and adequate supply-side response to rising demand. Despite increased inflationary pressure during Q2/2010, CPI inflation for the year as a whole is predicted to stay within the 5%±1% inflation targeting range.

The more conducive condition of the global economy and robust domestic economic fundamentals have enabled Indonesia to maintain a solid balance of payments position. The current account posted an estimated surplus, mainly in response to the steady improvement in the global economy and upward trend in global commodity prices. Estimates for the capital and financial account in Q2/2010 also point to a surplus. The surplus in the capital and financial account is again bolstered by renewed inflows of foreign capital in keeping with easing of global financial market jitters and improvement in Indonesia's credit rating outlook. Taken together, international reserves at end-June 2010 stood at 76.3 billion US dollars, equivalent to 5.9 months of imports and servicing of official external debt.
The rupiah exchange rate maintained an appreciating trend in response to the solid performance of the balance of payments and subdued risks. In comparison to Q1/2010, the average rate for the rupiah strengthened 1.58% (qtq) to Rp 9,110 to the US dollar. Accompanying the second quarter rupiah gains was a drop in volatility from 0.57% in Q1/2010 to 0.47% in Q2/2010. At the end of Q2/2010, the rupiah closed at Rp 9,060 to the US dollar, up 0.33% (ptp) from Q1/2010. The policy package launched by Bank Indonesia on 15 June 2010 has met with generally positive responses from domestic and international market actors, in turn easing pressure on the rupiah and contributing to more robust monetary management and financial market deepening.

Financial markets showed overall improved performance during Q2/2010, despite coming under pressure in May 2010. Conditions on the government securities and capital markets have progressively improved in the wake of pressures in May 2010 from negative sentiments over the European debt crisis. Key to the gains on the capital and government securities markets in Q2/2010 were renewed inflows of foreign investor funds and the subsiding of the stock market bubble. Conditions on the interbank money market reflected adequate levels of liquidity during Q2/2010.  The widening of the overnight interbank interest rate corridor on 17 June 2010 helped to ease the overnight rate. Improvement in global conditions and domestic fundamentals has also brought improvement in monetary policy transmission.  Reflecting this is the downward movement in bank deposit and lending rates accompanied by rising credit expansion, estimated at 18.6% in June 2010. 
At the micro level, conditions in the national banking system are stable. Reflecting this is the still comfortable level of the capital adequacy ratio (CAR) at 17.8% in May 2010. Similarly, the gross non-performing loans (NPLs) ratio remains subdued at 3.6% with the net ratio at 1%. Furthermore, liquidity in the banking system, including the interbank money market, has progressively improved alongside continued growth in depositor funds.

On 5 July 2010, the Bank Indonesia Board of Governors decided to maintain the BI Rate at 6.5% with an interest rate corridor on the overnight interbank market at +/- 100 bps of the BI Rate set as the operational target for monetary policy. Key to this decision was the assessment that the 6.5% level in the BI Rate remains consistent with achievement of the 5%±1% inflation target for 2010. The present monetary policy stance is also regarded conducive to the economic recovery process against the background of high global risks fuelled by the debt crisis in some European economies.