The domestic economy is forging ahead with support from the buoyant performance of the global economy. Economic activity in Indonesia showed significant improvement during Q4/2009. Quarterly growth in the economy reached an estimated 5.4% (yoy), bringing growth for 2009 overall to 4.5% (yoy). Conditions in the economy, marked by growing optimism, support a more upbeat outlook compared to earlier forecasts. In 2010, the Indonesian economy is predicted to grow in the range of 5.5%-6.0% and in 2011 at 6.0%-6.5%. Price stability remains in safe territory, as reflected in the subdued movement in the CPI during Q1/2010. This is consistent with the prediction of no significant inflationary pressure arising at least during the first half of 2010. For the year as a whole, CPI inflation will come within the 5%±1% targeted range.

In the view of Bank Indonesia, the global economy is in recovery and gathering momentum. Advanced economies, led by the US and Japan, are showing steady improvement. Similarly, economic recovery in non-Japan Asia, most importantly China and India, is forging ahead. In other developments, signs are emerging of improvement in European economies, albeit on a limited scale. The resolution of the Greece crisis has so far met with positive response among economic actors, with impact limited to financial markets.

The recovery in the global economy coupled with improved perceptions of risk has fuelled optimism on financial and commodity markets. Reflecting this are gains in global stock indices and an upward trend in international market commodity prices. Foreign capital flows continued to pour into emerging markets in keeping with improving risk perceptions, a condition that has bolstered currency appreciation in the region. Rising optimism over the global economic recovery and strengthening of global demand spurred price increases across a range of commodities. The price increases alongside appreciation in the currency have not so far triggered any significant rise in global inflation, particularly in advanced nations. With the world economy not yet fully recovered to normal, monetary authorities in developed nations in particular have leaned towards an accommodative monetary policy stance. Signals of monetary tightening are more evident on emerging markets due to rising inflationary pressures fuelled by high rates of economic expansion.

Domestic economic performance in Q1-2010 could potentially surpass earlier forecasts. During Q1/2010, the domestic economy charted an estimated 5.7% growth (yoy). This performance was bolstered by the following factors. First, stronger export performance is forecasted in keeping with the improvement in the global economy and rising international commodity prices. Second, consumption is predicted to remain strong, bolstered by safe levels of public purchasing power and consumer expectations. Third, in keeping with rising exports and household consumption, stronger recovery in investment is forecasted with support from various Government actions to fast-track infrastructure projects. Added to this, the improved investment climate in 2010 is also supported by the S&P decision to raise Indonesia's sovereign credit rating from BB- to BB. With this rating upgrade, Indonesia is now just 1 notch below investment grade. Fourth, in line with more robust external side performance, more vigorous growth is forecasted for some sectors, most importantly manufacturing and trade. Manufacturing growth has picked up in response to stronger performance in export-oriented manufacturing and the automotive industry. At the same time, more vigorous trade sector growth is consistent with mounting activity in exports and imports and stronger manufacturing performance. Nevertheless, various issues remain that pose challenges to higher growth, particularly in regard to measures to accelerate infrastructure programmes and make optimum use of opportunities from the launching of the ASEAN-China Free Trade Agreement (AC-FTA).

The strengthening of the economy is also visible in the steady improvement in economic performance at the regional level. Economic performance in the regions was led by Sumatra, Kalimantan, Sulawesi, Maluku and Papua (Kali-Sulampua) and Jakarta. Other regions (Java, Bali and Nusa Tenggara or Jabalnustra), however, reported slowing economic activity. Buoyant economic performance in the regions is driven by higher exports, investments and consumption. Export performance in individual regions has risen on higher exports of mainstay commodities, such as mining products and CPI in Sumatra and Kali-Sulampua and chemicals in the Jabalnustra region. In analysis by major export destinations, exports from individual regions have shifted from Japan, America and Europe as in the past to ASEAN and China, due to the more advanced recovery in these economies. Sumatra and Kali-Sulampua have even increased their share of exports to India, particularly for CPO and coal. Indications point to strengthening investment in line with the mounting pace of economic activity. Reflecting this is the positive growth in the indicators for cement consumption growth and capital goods imports. In the area of Regional Government investment, increases have been made in capital expenditures. The higher investment has been channelled mainly into infrastructure projects, such as construction of roads, dams, bridges and airports. In analysis by business category, the industry sector has picked up in response to improving domestic and external demand. More robust industry performance is reflected in production capacity expansion and higher raw materials imports in all regions. In the mining sector, performance has climbed largely from increased production of non-oil and gas mining products led by coal and copper. In contrast, oil and natural gas production continues on a slowing trend.

Concerning prices, inflation remained at modest levels in Q1/2010. Low inflationary pressure in Q1/2010 was indicated by March 2010 deflation at 0.14% (mtm), bringing annual CPI inflation to 3.43% (yoy). The success in curbing inflation at this low level is partly attributable to the appreciation in the rupiah and adequate levels of supply in responding to increased demand. Besides this, the low inflation in March 2010 also resulted from a moderation of inflationary pressures from volatile foods (mainly rice), due to the onset of the harvest season in some regions, and minimum inflationary pressure from administered prices.

The balance of payments maintained an estimated solid position in Q1/2010, supported by recovery in the world economy. Projections point to a current account surplus, consistent with the steady improvement in exports, particularly of resource-based commodities including coal and copper. Conversely, imports have also climbed in response to more robust domestic and export demand. The capital and financial account similarly recorded an estimated Q1/2010 surplus on the strength of capital inflows and issuance of government foreign currency bonds. Risk indicators for Indonesia have improved, as reflected in the all-time low in the credit default swap (CDS) indicator for Indonesia, narrowing yield spread for Indonesia Government Bonds over US Treasury Notes and the upgrading of Indonesia's rating.  Taken together, international reserves at end-March 2010 stood at 71.8 billion US dollars, equivalent to 5.8 months of imports and servicing of official external debt.

The solid performance in the balance of payments underpinned an appreciating trend in the rupiah. Measured as an average for Q1/2010, the rupiah appreciated by an overall 2.2% to Rp 9,254/USD. At end Q1/2010, the rupiah stood at Rp 9,090/USD, having gained 3.7% (point to point). The strengthening of the rupiah was supported by conducive conditions in macroeconomic fundamentals, reflected in healthy performance in the balance of payments and improving risk perceptions. Other support for rupiah appreciation came from the continued attractiveness of returns on rupiah placements, reflected in uncovered parity (UIP), covered interest parity (CIP) and the relatively high yield spread on Indonesia Government Bonds surpassing yields in other countries in the region. The appreciation in the rupiah was also accompanied by stable level of exchange rate volatility at 0.57% compared to the Q4/2009 level of 0.56%.

Financial sector performance has picked up in line with the recovery in the global and domestic economy. The JSX Composite Index mounted significantly in Q1/2010 with gains at 10.2%. This index performance was the highest for any country in the region. Factors driving the JSX Composite gains include the brightening outlook for the Indonesian economy, and with it, reduced perceptions of risk, improvement in the credit rating and high returns on rupiah placements. Also reflecting this was movement in other financial indicators, such as declining yield on government securities. Considerable excess liquidity remains on the interbank money market, which has pushed the overnight interbank rate closer to the lower BI Rate corridor.  The Bank Indonesia decision to lengthen the maturities of SBIs for reasons including financial deepening proved successful, as indicated by the narrowing of the high-low interest rate spread on the overnight interbank market. Added to this, the proportion of SBIs in the 3-month tenor soared to 67.0$ from 24.64% at the end of the preceding quarter. Consistent with the diminishing perceptions of bank risks, deposit and lending rates saw further decline although less than expected. Looking forward, monetary policy transmission is predicted to improve in line with strengthening optimism of the banking system in the condition of the economy.

At the micro level, conditions in the national banking system remain stable. Reflecting this is the still comfortable level of the capital adequacy ratio (CAR) at 19.3% in February. Similarly, the gross non-performing loans (NPLs) ratio remains below 4% with the net ratio at 1%. Besides this, banking liquidity improved further, including liquidity on the interbank money market. Bank depositor funds similarly recorded growth.

The improvements in the global and domestic economy during Q1/2010 are forecasted to carry forward into the future. This reinforces the confidence of Bank Indonesia in a more robust outlook for the Indonesian economy compared to earlier forecasts. Economic growth in 2010 is predicted in the 5.0%-6.0% range, up from the originally projected 5.0%-5.5%. The economy improved not only from the continued strength of consumption, but also higher exports in line with the global economic recovery. Rising demand accompanied by improvement in the investment climate is expected to drive significant growth in investment. The improvement in the economy is forecasted to carry forward into 2011 with growth possibly reaching 6.0%-6.5%. Rising demand matched by capacity for supply-side response is expected to keep future inflationary pressures at a modest level. A complete elaboration of the medium-term outlook for the economy is presented the Indonesian Economic Review 2009, accessible on the Bank Indonesia website.

On 6 April 2010, the Bank Indonesia Board of Governors decided to maintain the BI Rate at 6.5% with an interest rate corridor at +/- 50 bps around the BI Rate. Key to this decision was the assessment that the 6.5% level in the BI Rate remains consistent with achievement of the 5%+1% inflation target for 2010. The present monetary policy stance is also regarded conducive to the economic recovery process and operation of the bank intermediation function.