Global indicators point to continued progress in world economic recovery despite heightened risks on global financial markets from the Greek debt crisis. Reflecting this was improvement in advanced economies, led by the US and Japan, alongside the brisk economic growth in emerging market nations. In the US, improving economic conditions are visible in strengthening domestic demand and rising imports. The European economy is also regaining ground, as reflected in slower contraction of retail sales, expansion in industry and rising consumer confidence. In Japan, improvement in the economy is being driven more by exports. China remains the leading growth economy among the emerging markets, despite initial signs of slowing in response to tightened lending. The present recovery in the global economy now faces risks from the debt crisis that has now hit a number of European nations and is ongoing.  

The continued strength of global economic recovery has been matched by steady improvement in the Indonesian economy. Exports are forging ahead, buoyed by more optimistic developments in manufactured exports in keeping with the more upbeat condition of the global economy. Industries reporting significant growth include textiles, garments, transportation equipment and the chemicals subsector. Production has responded to rising exports with increased utilisation, particularly in export-oriented industries. Investment is also picking up as reflected in the rising imports of raw materials and capital goods as well as rising cement and industrial electricity consumption.  In analysis by sector, economic performance was driven mainly by significantly gains in the trade, hotels and restaurants (THR) sector. Performance in THR was also bolstered by activity in other sectors, such as agriculture, manufacturing and imports. Outside the THR sector, another vibrant area of activity was the transport and communications sector. The upbeat pace of economic activity is supported by higher levels of bank financing, mainly in investment credit.

Prices movements indicated subdued inflationary pressure during May 2010. Inflation was driven mainly by the volatile foods category (rice and miscellaneous seasonings) as a result of disruptions in supply and distribution. On the other hand, only mild inflationary pressure was recorded in core items and administered prices. The absence of strategic price decisions by the government helped maintain low inflationary pressure in administered prices.  Inflation in the consumer price index (CPI) reached 0.29% (mtm) or 4.16% (yoy). These developments brought inflation for the January to May 2010 period to 1.44% (ytd).

Indonesia's balance of payments showed solid performance in estimated figures despite heightened uncertainties over the Greek debt crisis. The robust condition of Indonesia's economic fundamentals again contributed to the strong balance of payments. The ongoing improvement in domestic economic performance and outlook has helped attract foreign direct investment (FDI). In the current account, the more vigorous growth in export revenues compared to imports produced a surplus. Export revenues during the first 4 months of 2010 came close to levels preceding the 2008 crisis, despite slowing growth in April 2010. The steepest fall in April 2010 was recorded in exports to Europe, which came down 23%. Among Indonesia's leading export commodities to Europe, crude palm oil (CPO) plunged significantly as a result of environmental campaigns by NGOs in Europe that have prompted a boycott of CPO products from Indonesia. In the capital and financial account, inflows of portfolio capital were impacted by negative sentiment over the European debt crisis. In response, international reserves at 31 May 2010 stood at 74.6 billion US dollars, equivalent to 5.87 months of imports and servicing of official foreign debt.

Widespread uncertainty on global financial market over the debt crisis in some European economies put added pressure on exchange rates in emerging Asia, including Indonesia. This brought a halt to the appreciating trend in the rupiah under way since early 2010. During May, the average value of the rupiah was down 1.52% at Rp 9,167 to the US dollar compared to Rp 9,028 to the US dollar one month earlier. With financial markets in the region still susceptible to negative sentiment from various quarters, the rupiah closed lower at Rp 9,175 to the US dollar, having sustained 1.77% correction from the previous month's close. Even so, when compared to the end of 2009, the rupiah still managed 2.53% appreciation in monthly average level or 2.72% gain point to point.

The turmoil on global financial markets has also dented financial market performance in Indonesia. Negative sentiment was sparked by pessimism among financial market actors over efforts to resolve the debt problems of the PIIGS nations (Portugal, Italy, Ireland, Greece and Spain). Slow responses in resolving the crisis exacerbated risks and uncertainties on financial markets. Global liquidity is tightening further with the effects felt most in Europe due to downgrading of some sovereign ratings that has triggered decline in asset values and heightened counterparty risks. Reflecting the crunch on global money markets is the widening spread in the 3-month tenor Overnight Index Swap (OIS) over the 3-month LIBOR. This ultimately triggered flight to quality by foreign investors and sent share prices tumbling in almost all markets in the region. As a result, the JSX Composite Index (JCI) sustained 5.8% correction to close at 2,796.96 at end-May 2010. During May 2010, share volume averaged Rp 5.1 trillion in daily trading, largely unchanged from Rp 5.2 trillion the month before. The financial market turmoil during May 2010 has also begun spreading to the market for Indonesian government securities, as evident in increased yield evenly distributed across all tenors.

From the micro banking perspective, conditions in the banking system are comfortably secure alongside improvement in the bank intermediary function. Banking system stability in Indonesia is now sufficiently robust to anticipate contagion from the debt crisis in Europe. This is borne out in the high capital adequacy ratio (CAR) for the banking system, reported in the most recent data at 19.2%, in addition to the subdued level of non-performing loans (NPLs) gross at below 5%. Improvement in the bank intermediation function is reflected in credit expansion, recorded as of end-May 2010 at 17.6% (yoy). This credit growth remains within the limits of the lending plans described in Bank Business Plans and is consistent with the growing confidence of economic actors in the improving outlook for the Indonesian economy.

In the Board of Governors Meeting convened on 3 June 2010, Bank Indonesia decided to hold the BI Rate at 6.5%. This decision was taken after a comprehensive evaluation of the latest developments and outlook for the economy, which is now showing steady improvement. In the opinion of the Board of Governors, the BI Rate at this level is consistent with achievement of the 5%±1% inflation target in 2010 and 2011 and remains conducive to strengthening the process of economic recovery. This decision is also consistent with measures to safeguard domestic financial stability amid the escalation of risks and uncertainties caused by the debt crisis in Greece and a number of other European nations.