Developments in the global economy suggest a gathering momentum in the recovery process, although still daunted by risks. In developed nations, various indicators of macroeconomic recovery have shown an improving trend. Government-sponsored stimulus packages and financial sector stabilisation programmes have successfully bolstered public confidence, and in turn strengthened consumption. Conditions on credit markets have also begun to improve in an added development encouraging greater private consumption. Despite this, stubbornly high levels of unemployment pose risks daunting the economic recovery process in these nations. On the other hand, economic recovery is gaining momentum in emerging market countries, led by China, India and Korea. Investment activity in China, under way since the beginning of the year, is supported by a fiscal stimulus through infrastructure spending and brisk credit expansion Resurgent domestic demand in these Asian economies has stimulated improved economic performance in other countries in the region. Despite this, the economic improvement in some emerging market countries is not yet regarded sufficient to compensate for the slowdown in advanced economies. In response to these developments, further contraction is predicted in the global economy, although at a lesser pace.

Expectations of world economic recovery have fuelled positive developments on global financial markets. Global financial sector performance showed steady gains throughout Q2/2009. Stock markets in developed economies recorded index gains on the back of positive sentiment linked to improvement in bank performance in the wake of the stress tests, optimism for stabilisation of the financial sector and economic conditions and positive performance reported in financial statements published by some world financial institutions. Banking sector conditions have shown improvement, as reflected in a relaxation of lending standards. These financial market developments in advanced nations have in turn impacted financial markets in the region. Despite this, financial market developments took a downturn near the end of the period, triggered by negative sentiment related to stubbornly high levels of unemployment in the United States and Europe.

The improving trend in the global economy has had a positive impact on Indonesia’s economic performance. The impact of strengthening demand in trading partners, led by China and India, has boosted Indonesian exports of commodities such as CPO, coal and copper,. Despite the steady improvement, the lack of recovery in the global economy means that exports continue to suffer contraction. Concerning domestic demand, the flagging pace of private consumption has been mitigated by the presidential election and the payout of the 13th month salary to civil servants. Investment activity remains limited under the present conditions of continued weak demand and low levels of capacity utilisation. In view of these developments, economic growth in Q2/2009 is estimated at 3.7%-4.0%.

In regard to prices, the declining inflation trend is set to continue. During June 2009, consumer goods prices recorded 0.11% inflation (mtm), considerably below the historical level and earlier projections. Increases in some international food commodity prices were again offset by appreciation in the rupiah, thus keeping a lid on increases in domestic prices. Besides the appreciation in the rupiah, improving expectations of inflation bolstered by the accelerated pace of disinflation brought down the rate of core inflation. Measures to safeguard adequate supplies of food staples also helped maintain low inflation in Q2/2009. Taken together, cumulative inflation in the CPI measured 0.21% (ytd) or 3.65% (yoy). 
 Rising commodity prices and strengthening demand in emerging market countries also bolstered the balance of payments, which is performing ahead of earlier predictions. Balance of payments performance has strengthened on the back of a larger than expected surplus in the current account. Non-oil and gas exports have received a boost from rising global market commodity prices, led by mining commodities and crude palm oil, and also from resurgent demand in emerging market nations and especially China and India. In the capital and financial account, portfolio investments again recorded a surplus. Improving conditions on global financial markets and sustained positive perceptions of the domestic economy have prompted renewed growth in portfolio capital inflows. However, following the capital reversal that hit domestic financial markets in mid-June 2009, portfolio investment levels for Q2/2009 were not as high as predicted. Inflows for direct investment are also estimated to have climbed in response to growing exploration activity by oil and natural gas companies. Furthermore, the confidence that has been maintained in the domestic economic outlook and the freeing up of global financial markets has led to higher than forecasted disbursements on private foreign debt. As a result, international reserves reached US$57.58 billion at end-June/2009, equivalent to 5.6 months of imports and servicing of official debt.

Improvement in the balance of payments and positive sentiment on the global market have brought about exchange rate appreciation. Compared to other countries in the region, the rupiah maintained the second highest rate of appreciation after the Korean won. Averaged over Q2/2009, the rupiah gained 9.99% on the back of increased supply of foreign currency in response to foreign capital inflows. Optimism for global economic recovery alongside carefully managed domestic economic fundamentals, reflected in the balance of payments surplus and attractive yields on rupiah instruments, has stimulated risk appetite for financial assets in emerging markets, including Indonesia. Despite this, negative sentiment over global economic developments prompted a slight drop in the value of the rupiah at end-Q2/2009 compared to early June 2009. 

In the financial sector, global developments and conducive domestic macroeconomic indicators have had a positive effect on the domestic financial sector. The stock market charted overall index gains during Q2/2009 despite temporary capital reversal near the end of the quarter that prompted a dip in the stock index. Improvement in domestic fundamentals and rising global commodity prices have paved the way for brisk share buying activity by foreign and domestic investors. On the bond market, yield on Indonesian government securities eased in line with the downward movement in the monetary policy rate and resurgent interest among foreign investors. Despite this, Government Securities yield in longer tenors (above 15 years) remains high, reflecting strong risk perceptions. 
 In the banking sector, the national banking system is in comparatively stable condition despite the limited banking response to monetary easing. At the micro level, conditions in the Indonesian banking system were again stable, as indicated by the safe level of the capital adequacy ratio (CAR) at a high 17.3% in May 2009. Alongside this, the gross non-performing loans (NPLs) ratio has been held below 5% with net NPLs less than 2%. Banking liquidity, including liquidity on the interbank money market, is steadily improving alongside growth in depositor funds. Despite this, bank interest rates again showed only limited response. The base lending rate response to the 250 bps reduction in the BI Rate from December 2008 to June 2009 measured no more than about 45 bps in figures for May 2009. In a related development, bank loan disbursements for the position at May 2009 saw further contraction at 1.1% (ytd). Even so, liquidity in the economy was adequate. Although the expansion in monetary aggregates (cash outside banks and M1) remains very thin, calculations based on fundamentals indicate that the trend in monetary aggregates is still commensurate to the needs of the economy. With loan interest rates declining at a slower pace and the very limited rate of credit expansion, indications are emerging of a more intensive shift under way in business towards non-bank financing alternatives, such as bond issues.

Looking forward, the economic growth outlook is better than originally predicted. In the short-term, economic projections will be strongly influenced by global developments. The predicted contraction in exports for the year as a whole is expected to be offset by a surge in private consumption from the national elections. Given the bigger than expected impact from the election of parliamentary and local assembly candidates in Q1/2009, the 2009 presidential polls are predicted to contribute significantly to private consumption. While purchasing power has yet to show significant improvement, private consumption is forecasted to maintain brisk growth in 2009 from the knock-on effects of the national elections. Against this background, the economy has potential to chart higher than projected growth for 2009 as a whole. Indonesia's GDP is forecasted at 3.5%-4.0% growth by end-2009, with a bias towards the upper limit of this band.

Indonesia's balance of payments is predicted to chart a surplus for 2009 overall, strengthened by improvement in global economic conditions, rising commodity prices and ongoing stabilisation of global financial markets. Exports are predicted to improve in response to the more evenly distributed improvement in the global economy across the world's regions since Q3/2008 and the ongoing rise in world commodity prices. In the capital and financial account, foreign capital inflows in portfolio and direct investments are set to continue in line with optimism for world economic recovery alongside more conducive conditions on global financial markets. In addition, capital inflows in the public sector are expected to shore up performance in the capital and financial account.

After factoring in these developments, the Bank Indonesia Board of Governors Meeting on 03 July 2009 decided to lower the BI Rate by 25 bps from 7.0% to 6.75%. This decision is expected to bolster measures for sustaining optimism in domestic economic growth.

Looking ahead, monetary policy will seek to maintain a balance between bolstering the domestic economy amid the persistent sluggishness of the global economy and maintaining macroeconomic stability over the medium-term with the looming increase in inflationary pressure in 2010. Accordingly, future monetary policy will pursue a more prudent course in view of the progressively limited room for monetary relaxation. 