The continuing downturn in the global economy took an increasingly heavy toll on the Indonesian economy in Q1/2009, necessitating a downward revision in the economic growth forecast for Indonesia. This slowing trend is explained not only by flagging exports, but also weakening public purchasing power. Despite this, economic activity fuelled by the political campaign activities for the national election is expected to keep the domestic economy from further decline. Looking forward, the economy in 2009 continues to be daunted by uncertainty over global economic recovery, and therefore economic growth in Indonesia is forecasted below the 4.0%-5.0% level predicted at the beginning of the year. In April 2009, following an assessment of the current economic conditions and outlook, Bank Indonesia lowered the BI Rate a further 25 bps to 7.5%, representing the fifth consecutive cut in the BI Rate since December 2008. Measured cumulatively for the December 2008-April 2009 period, the BI Rate came down by a total of 175 bps.

Estimated Q1/2009 growth in the Indonesian economy reached 4.6%. On the expenditure side, decline was reported in all growth components, led by exports. Despite this, economic activity during the election period, fuelled by political campaigns and the organisation of elections throughout Indonesia, is believed to have prevented further decline in private consumption. In analysis by sector, estimates suggest that the steepest downturns took place in industry and mining. In contrast, non-tradable sectors, such as transport and communications and the electricity, gas and water utilities sector, maintained brisk growth accompanied by a slowing trend. In disaggregation by region, falling exports have been the key factor in the economic slowdown in regions such as Sumatra, Kalimantan, Sulawesi, Maluku and Papua.

The downward inflationary trend continues. Inflationary pressure in Q1/2009 slowed further to 0.36% (quarterly, q-t-q) or measured annually to 7.92% (y-o-y). Inflationary pressure eased mainly in response to the ongoing first round and second round effects of the cut in fuel prices. Added contribution to low inflationary pressure came from improvement in inflation expectations and softening domestic demand. Alongside this, similarly low pressure was reported from administered prices and volatile foods, with domestic food crop production maintained at adequate levels. 
Concerning external performance, the Q1/2009 balance of payments recorded an estimated 3.5 billion US dollar surplus. Export volume of some mainstay commodities, such as palm oil, copper and paper, maintained a positive trend. However, other commodities, such as coal and chemicals, faltered in the face of weakening global demand. Alongside this, imports of raw materials and capital goods for domestic industry came down significantly, due to slumping domestic demand. In the financial account, the issuance of global bonds by the Government helped to generate account surplus. Under these conditions, international reserves in Q1/2009 reached an estimated USD54.8 billion, equivalent to 5.9 months of imports and servicing of official external debt.

On the financial market, downward pressure continued although the end of the quarter was marked by some improvement. These pressures are related to lack of improvement in corporate performance and still heightened perceptions of risk shared by owners of capital. Nevertheless, at the end of Q1/2009, the financial market saw a rebound of positive sentiment from the more robust international reserves position following the issue of Indonesian Government global bonds, the expanded Bilateral Swap Arrangement (BSA) with the Government of Japan and the signature of a Bilateral Currency Swap Arrangement (BSCA) with the central bank of China.

Amid the steady deterioration in global economic conditions and weakening inflationary pressure, Bank Indonesia is maintaining a pro-growth focus while seeking to avoid further losses in public purchasing power. The various monetary policy actions pursued by Bank Indonesia are designed to support recovery in the real sector with focus on MSMEs and thus bolster domestic economic growth. 
Besides monetary policy relaxation, Bank Indonesia launched supplementary policy packages aimed at accelerating disbursement of bank credit and mitigating credit risk. These supplementary packages include early restructuring of the banking system, request for Government loan guarantees for strategic projects, such as clean water, electricity, housing and road and bridge infrastructure financed by the State Budget, and facilitation to match banks with sectors offering potential for strengthening the banking intermediation function. Vigorous efforts were pursued in support of the banking business activity focus on MSMEs and the linkage program for cooperation between commercial banks and rural banks or micro financial institutions such as cooperatives and Islamic community trusts (baitul maal wa tamwil). These measures are expected to provide added support for people's livelihoods and prevent further slowing in the economy. 

Looking ahead, the Indonesian economy in 2009 will be strongly influenced by the dynamics of the global economy. Indonesia’s economic growth forecast has been revised downwards from the 4.0%-5.0% initially predicted for 2009. Even so, Bank Indonesia believes that international commodity prices have now reached a trough with signs pointing to a turnaround that could bolster prices and in turn support export growth. In other developments, the world economic slowdown and falling aggregate demand have eased inflationary pressure. For the future, the prospects of further economic slowdown in 2009 augur for a sustained downward trend with inflation on track for the lower end of the 5%-7% range.

Indonesia’s banking industry is predicted to feel the effects of the global financial crisis and world economic slowdown. Nevertheless, the national banking industry will still retain considerable resilience, as reflected in the CAR and NPL key banking indicators. The capital adequacy ratio (CAR) will remain strong at 17.7%. Banking liquidity is also predicted to improve on the strength of brisk 19.8% (y-o-y) growth in depositor funds.  Despite this, the slowing trend in credit expansion is set to persist due to the cautious stance adopted by banks amid the present uncertain economic outlook.
After factoring in these various developments, the Bank Indonesia Board of Governors decided to lower the BI Rate by 25 bps in April 2009 to 7.50%. Bank Indonesia will stay the course with monetary policy conducive to domestic demand while remaining committed to economic stability in the medium to long-term. On the operational level, further cuts in the BI Rate will be possible provided that the inflation outlook remains consistent with the medium-term inflation target. In banking, Bank Indonesia will keep pressing forward with the consolidation programme for a sound, strong and competitive banking system. In further actions, Bank Indonesia will maintain its focus on strengthening prudential management in the banking industry in order to weather the global crisis.