As 2010 drew to a close, a range of economic indicators pointed to sustained improvement in the economy. Economic growth is expected to reach about 6% with inflation running at 6.96%. Indonesia's balance of payments is also projected to chart a hefty surplus while the stable rupiah has maintained an appreciating trend, closing the year at Rp 9,010 to the US dollar. This buoyant growth has been bolstered by vibrant domestic demand led by consumption and investment. Also key to this performance is the global economic recovery led by emerging markets and Indonesia's prudently managed macroeconomic stability. Indonesian economy was also influenced by developments on the external side, particularly heavy inflows of foreign capital, amid ample liquidity in the domestic economy. An added complexity is the onset of progressively mounting inflationary pressure. These conditions led to formidable challenges in the national economy during 2010 and is expected to continue. Bank Indonesia has responded to the challenges by applying an appropriate combination of available instruments, instead of focusing on a single policy instrument. The monetary and macroprudential policy mix combining a range of instruments was announced in part in the policy package of 16 June 2010.  At the end of 2010, Bank Indonesia issued further monetary and banking policies with the objective of reinforcing monetary and financial system stability to support sustainable economic growth while also building resilience against possible economic shocks. These policies cover five key areas: reinforcement of monetary stability, promotion of bank intermediation, improvement in the banking system resiliency, improvement of macroprudential policies, and enhancement of banking supervision functions.

On the external side, the global economic recovery regained momentum as reflected in the improvement in the latest data on the global economy, although remained overshadowed by the crisis in Ireland. Leading economic indicators, such as retail sales and manufacturing output in advanced countries, showed renewed improvement accompanied by strengthening consumer confidence. Global inflationary pressure also began to mount, particularly in emerging countries.  Inflationary pressure in Japan has reached positive territory. In spite of these developments, the US still faces the looming threat of deflation as core inflation continued on a downward trend. Global economic data pointing to an ongoing recovery have sparked positive sentiment on global financial markets. Global commodity prices also steadily went up as the global economy gathered momentum. World oil prices surged on rising demand from advanced economies to cope with extreme weather, in addition to OPEC decision to maintain existing production quotas. At the same time, the banking crisis in Ireland triggered concerns that similar crises could hit the PIIGS nations, and particularly Spain and Portugal. Policy responses by central banks in advanced countries also directed towards keeping interest rates low. In contrast, emerging market economies had started to raise their policy rates and introduced policies to manage capital inflows and stabilise exchange rate.

From the domestic side, economic growth in Q4/2010 is projected to improve, compare to the preceding quarter, buoyed by vibrant household consumption and higher investment. The high rate of household consumption has been fuelled by strong purchasing power, adequate bank and non-bank financing, strong consumer confidence, and low prices of imported goods. At the same time, investment has forged ahead on the back of positive market perceptions, more financing support, low imports price due to appreciation in the rupiah, and the launching of pro-investment policies by the government. However, government consumption is estimated to have slowed in Q4/2010. This trend was also observed in export and import activity, although momentum remained strong. Taken together, the economy charted an estimated 6.1% growth in Q4/2010, bringing growth for the whole year to around 6%.  

CPI inflation in December 2010 was marked by strong pressure from the volatile foods category. Significant price increases for rice and chilli peppers boosted volatile foods inflation to 3.29% (mtm). Administered prices accounted for only a moderate contribution to inflation, due to the absence of government decisions to raise prices for strategic items. In addition, core inflation was subdued. The rising inflationary pressure at the end of the year was also driven by the seasonal factor of the Christmas and New Year festivities and school holidays. With these developments, CPI inflation in December 2010 reached 0.92% (mtm) or 6.96% (yoy). As a result, CPI inflation for 2010 overshot the targeted range of 5%±1%. This deviation is explained primarily by the non-fundamental factor of high volatile foods inflation caused by adverse weather conditions. Sharply rising volatile foods inflation has also been observed in other countries in the region. Nevertheless, pressure from fundamentals was relatively mild, as demonstrated by contained core inflation and also moderate inflation in administered prices. 

Indonesia's balance is expected to post a large surplus. Supporting this projection are high capital inflows, led by foreign direct investment (FDI) and portfolio investment. In the current account, exports remain strong although lower than previous quarter, while imports also slow, resulting in current account surplus. The current account for oil and gas came under pressure from the rising oil deficit, although this was offset by improved performance in the non-oil and gas. These developments boosted the international reserves position to 96.2 billion US dollars at end-December 2010, equivalent to 7.1 months of imports and servicing of official external debt. 

Against the background of Indonesia's strong external performance, the rupiah underwent further exchange rate appreciation accompanied by low volatility. At the end of year, the rupiah gained 4.4% (point tp point) to Rp 9,010 to the USD with lower volatility. The policies taken by Bank Indonesia for managing capital inflows and exchange rate stability through forex intervention and accumulation of international reserves had helped to foster positive expectations towards the economy. The rupiah underwent relatively mild appreciation compared to other currencies in the region, enabling Indonesia to maintain a competitive position.

Domestic financial market performance showed further improvement. Vibrant performance on the stock market was reflected in gains in the Jakarta Composite Index (JCI) on the back of improvement in domestic economic fundamentals and the upbeat financial outlook for listed companies. However, inflows of foreign capital on the stock and bond markets heightened the risk of capital reversal, with possible impact of price adjustment in securities prices. Improved financial market performance was also reflected in the progressively narrowing yield on Indonesian government securities, particularly for short tenors, with yield of one-year Indonesian government bonds has dropped to below the level of the BI Rate and Bank Indonesia Certificate (SBIs).  Regarding monetary policy transmission, bank interest rates eased further. A fall in deposit rates was more limited compare to credit rates. In the credit channel, credit growth followed an upward trend, driven mainly by performance in working capital credit although increased contributions were also evident from consumption and investment credit.

Financial system stability remained in check, reinforced by the strength of the banking sector in coping with various risks and sound intermediation function. This was indicated by the high bank capital adequacy ratio (CAR), recorded at 16.3% in November 2010, and subdued level of non-performing loans (NPLs) at below 5.0%. Improvement in the bank intermediation function was indicated by stronger credit expansion at 22.8% (yoy) at end-December 2010. The most important source of this growth was lending to MSMEs. So far, the Indonesian banking system has not been impacted by fallout from the debt crisis in Europe, due to the comparatively limited exposure of Indonesia's banks to the banking system in Euro countries.

In the Board of Governors' Meeting convened on 5 January 2011, Bank Indonesia decided to hold the BI Rate at 6.5%. Nevertheless, the Board is aware to an escalating trend in future inflationary pressure related to possible disruptions in supply of volatile foods and increases in administered prices. Concerning this, Bank Indonesia believes that any rise in inflation expectations can be contained with measures to improve effectiveness in production, distribution and availability of staple goods at the national and regional levels. Bank Indonesia will reinforce monetary and macroprudential policy mix introduced last year through balanced and measured optimisation of instruments. Bank Indonesia has launched a range of policies aimed at curbing liquidity and capital inflows, including an increased statutory reserve requirement (rupiah and foreign currency), the one-month holding period for Bank Indonesia Certificates (SBIs) and restrictions on short-term external borrowing by banks.