The process of global economic recovery continues to move forward, driven primarily by the economy of China. Bolstering China's economic might is brisk investment growth, high levels of foreign direct investment (FDI) and comparatively strong bank lending. Economies in advanced nations have begun moving in a more optimistic direction, led by the US and Japan. The turnaround in the two economies is reflected in the rise in retail sales and manufacturing activity, which has helped bring down levels of unemployment. On the other hand, Europe's economic recovery faces heavy challenges despite signs of renewed activity in manufacturing and initial improvement in retail sales. The fiscal crisis in Greece rooted in structural issues and high unemployment levels continue to daunt economic recovery in the region. 

The Greek crisis has brought added pressure to bear on global financial markets with the strongest effects felt in emerging markets, including Indonesia. The fiscal crisis in Greece has triggered risk aversion among investors, who are shying away from emerging market assets and shifting investments back into safe haven assets. Reflecting this are lower yields on US treasury bonds and appreciation in the US dollar. The present investor behaviour has resulted in higher risk premia and prompted a downturn on global stock markets.

Global liquidity is now in abundant supply, prompting some central banks to begin phasing out their quantitative easing policies. Clearer signals of monetary tightening have surfaced in Asia. This is evident from steps taken by China and India to increase the minimum reserve requirement. In coming months, emerging markets are likely to pursue a more rapid exit strategy compared to developed countries, with management of foreign capital flows likely to pose extraordinary challenges.
The steady improvement in the global economy has had a positive effect on growth in the domestic economy and particularly exports. Exports mounted significantly in Q4/2009 in response to the more upbeat condition of the global economy. Like before, the G3 nations dominate Indonesia's export markets with a combined share at about 40%. The steady improvement in the condition of the G3 economies has given an added boost to optimism for improvement in Indonesia's exports, which in turn will fuel manufacturing growth particularly in export-oriented industries. The rising income effect of manufacturing activity, spurred by exports, will strengthen public purchasing power. 

The more conducive condition of the economy will also bring added investment, led by investment in infrastructure such as roads, ports and energy. The government has also begun taking action to address various regulations hampering investment. The objective is for the real sector to take optimum advantage of the momentum of international and domestic economic recovery. These developments have engendered strong optimism for the domestic economic outlook in 2010. 
In regard to prices, inflationary pressure eased during February 2010. Measured for the month, inflation in February 2010 reached 0.30% (mtm), down from 0.84% (mtm) in the preceding month. All inflation determinants contributed to the modest inflation during the month under review. Food supply bottlenecks, which emerged briefly during January, were comparatively subdued in February. Added to this, pressure from imported inflation stayed low with the support of relative stability in the rupiah. Domestic demand has similarly not generated significant upward pressure on prices. Despite low monthly inflation, annual inflationary pressure was recorded in February at 3.81% (yoy), up slightly from the previous month's level of 3.72% (yoy). This is explained by the base effect factor from government decisions concerning administered prices last year. 

The latest global developments have strongly influenced the direction of Indonesia's balance of payments. Economic recovery led by the countries of Asia has boosted demand for exports of resource-based commodities. Support for stronger export performance has also come from improvement in manufactured exports, reflected in increased capacity utilisation in the manufacturing sector. With exports forging ahead, imports are also on the rise, although at a lesser pace. This augurs for an increased surplus in the current account. The speed of recovery in the Asian region has also given added attractiveness to investment in the region. In the wake of setbacks from negative sentiment triggered by external developments, such as the fiscal instability in Greece, fears of an asset price bubble in China and unclear direction of monetary policy in the US, foreign investor interest remains strong as reflected in the heavy surplus in the capital and financial account. The improvement in the investment climate is reflected in the mounting trend in investment visible in cash calls and loans. At the end of February 2010, international reserves stood at 69.7 billion US dollars, equivalent to 5.7 months of imports and servicing of official external debt. The solid condition of the balance of payments has kept the rupiah stable, despite pressure from negative external sentiment. During February 2010, the rupiah maintained more stable movement compared to the preceding month, reflecting in the drop in volatility from 0.96% in January to 0.3% in February. The rupiah closed February up 0.16% (p-t-p) at Rp 9,335 to the US dollar. 

In the domestic financial sector, financial market performance has held at generally stable levels. On the money market, banks were comparatively well supplied with liquidity. The abundance of short-term liquidity resulted in the overnight interbank rate easing to levels approaching the lower corridor of the BI Rate. On the stock market, the JSX Composite underwent contraction mainly in response to negative external sentiment. The negative sentiment dragging down the JSX Composite is explained, among others, by the monetary tightening in China, worries over fiscal sustainability in Greece and lack of a clear global exit strategy. On the government securities market, yield moved in different directions according to individual tenor. Yields on short-term Government Securities eased further, contrasting with increases observed in medium and long tenor instruments. This development was linked mainly to unsettled external factors and the early effects of rising inflation expectations in 2010. Developments on the mutual funds market largely tracked performance in underlying assets. The indices for equity and mixed funds saw steep correction at 1.6% and 0.7% in contrast to the index for fixed income funds, which mounted further by 0.5%. 

Monetary policy transmission in the financial sector has been limited. Although deposit and loan interest rates are in decline, the scale of lending remains limited. In January 2010, credit recorded negative growth, despite the positive growth measured on an annual scale. Looking forward, the downward trend in loan interest rates is expected to promote stronger credit expansion in 2010.
On the micro level, conditions in the national banking system remain stable. Reflecting this is the comfortably safe level of the capital adequacy ratio (CAR) alongside low non-performing loans (NPLs). In further developments, liquidity in the banking system, including the interbank money market, has progressively improved in tandem with growth in depositor funds. 

On 4 March 2010, the Board of Governors Meeting at Bank Indonesia decided to hold the BI Rate at 6.5%. The reasoning in this decision is that the 6.5% rate is consistent with the 5% ± 1% inflation target for 2010 and the current monetary policy stance is seen as conducive to economic recovery and the operation of the banking intermediation function.