The global economic crisis has taken a more severe turn with impact surpassing original predictions. Latest developments indicate that almost all developed nations and some developing countries will see significant GDP contraction during 2009. The liquidity crunch is also forecasted to keep bearing down on global financial markets in consequence of the ongoing deleveraging process in some developed economies.

In response to these developments, Bank Indonesia predicts that in 2009 the Indonesian economy will grow 4%-5%, with the risk of downward bias in the event of further global deterioration. Slowing export growth will be the primary cause of weakening economic performance in 2009. The major source of economic growth momentum this year will be domestic demand, driven mainly by private consumption bolstered by increased provincial minimum wage levels, expenditures related to central and regional government social policies and election-related spending by political parties. Alongside this, investment will benefit from Central Government capital expenditures integral to the fiscal stimulus and infrastructure construction, as well as Regional Government capital expenditures.

With the global economy and commodity prices in decline, inflationary pressure in Indonesia has begun to ease, with this trend predicted to carry forward in 2009. If the downward movement in prices for commodities, subsidised fuels and rice maintains a favourable trend, there is a strong likelihood of achieving the lower limit of the 5%-7% inflation projection for 2009. There are growing indications of future easing of inflationary pressures. Weakening domestic demand, steeper decline in international commodity prices (foodstuffs and energy) and adequately maintained supply of energy and staples are among the factors supporting the easing of inflationary pressures. Furthermore, the stronger than expected plunge in international crude prices could pave the way for further cuts in subsidised fuel prices. This in turn could push down prices for fuel-related items, such as transport fares.

In related developments, the average rupiah exchange rate appreciated further in January 2009, despite some weakening near month-end. The rupiah came under short-term pressure from external conditions marked by uncertainty over the economic outlook in various regions and turbulence on global financial markets. Bank Indonesia will stay the course with stabilisation of the rupiah to avoid excessive forex market volatility.

Amid these economic developments and with inflationary pressures in decline, Bank Indonesia is focusing its energies on sustaining domestic economic growth. In so doing, Bank Indonesia is maintaining a close watch on inflation, macroeconomic stability and the medium-term stability of the financial sector. Bank Indonesia is pursuing a series of monetary policy actions to prevent further losses in the real sector.

In the decision of the Board of Governors’ Meeting in February 2009, Bank Indonesia lowered the BI Rate by a further 50 bps from 8.75% to 8.25%, the third such action since December 2008. Besides cutting the BI Rate, Bank Indonesia will continue to optimise the use of all monetary instruments at its disposal, such as Open Market Operations (OMOs), while maintaining stability on the rupiah and forex markets. Added to this, the monetary policy relaxation has been accompanied by Bank Indonesia actions to promote bank lending to productive sectors within the limits of prudential banking. This measure is expected to deliver a boost to the domestic economy that will prevent steeper decline.

Banking indicators point to response to the BI Rate cut in time deposit and lending rates, albeit on a limited scale.  The downward movement in interest rates is also expected to ease supply constraints on bank lending. Regarding the business community, the lower interest rates are expected to counter business pessimism over the economic outlook.   

The Indonesian banking system remains in solid shape with the Capital Adequacy Ratio (CAR) and Non-Performing Loans (NPLs) within safe limits. Various measures to reduce the segmentation in banking liquidity have also shown results, reflected in renewed improvement in liquidity flows on the interbank money market compared to a few months before. 

Looking forward, the Board of Governors of Bank Indonesia will stay the course with a pro-growth policy while keeping a close watch on macroeconomic stability. Further easing of inflationary pressures will allow room for more cuts in the BI Rate. Support for lowering of the BI Rate will also come from other actions for improvement and strengthening of the financial sector, including improvements to the bank supervision system. Bank Indonesia will continue its efforts to expand the banking sector role as a source of business financing and momentum for economic growth. 