The Indonesian economy in quarter IV 2013 and January 2014 demonstrated that the stabilisation policy instituted by Bank Indonesia in conjunction with the Government in the middle of 2013 is beginning to bare fruit and guide the economy in the desired direction. The anticipative response taken by Bank Indonesia through an optimal policy mix is successfully easing inflationary pressures back to within the target corridor of 4.5±1% in 2014 and 4.0±1% in 2015. Furthermore, Bank Indonesia policy, which interacts with consolidative fiscal policy and is buttressed by intensive coordination, also helped reduce the current account deficit to a more sustainable level, while accompanied by a measured process of moderation in terms of economic growth.  Solid economic performance was achieved during the final quarter of 2013, which is expected to form a sustainable basis for future economic growth looking ahead.
 
Economic growth in quarter IV 2013 exceeded Bank Indonesia’s projections, bolstered by a more balanced structure. The economy expanded from 5.63% (yoy) in the third quarter of 2013 to 5.72% (yoy) in the reporting period on the back of a surge in real exports in line with strong demand from trading partners in advanced countries. Meanwhile, sluggish household consumption and investment, particularly non-construction investment, evidenced moderating domestic demand. Consequently, economic growth in Indonesia for the year 2013 as a whole achieved 5.78%, which is comparatively high among similarly rated countries.
 
The current account deficit was reduced to a more sustainable level, amounting to just 1.98% of GDP in quarter IV 2013 compared to 3.85% in the preceding quarter, which is lower than Bank Indonesia’s preliminary projections. The reduction in the current account deficit was made possible by an increase in exports in line with stronger demand for manufactured goods from the US and Japan, a slower decline in the prices of exported commodities and an upswing in exports of natural resources in anticipation of the new Minerals and Coal Mining (Minerba) Act. In addition, the smaller current account deficit was also the result of a slowdown in imports in harmony with moderating domestic demand and rupiah depreciation. Concomitantly, the financial and capital account surplus swelled to offset the current account deficit and led to a surplus in the balance of payments in the final quarter of 2013, after registering a deficit in the previous three quarters. Favourable conditions in the external sector persisted into January 2014, indicated by an increase in the foreign exchange reserves held by Indonesia from those in December 2013 totalling US$ 100 billion, equivalent to 5.7 months of imports or 5.6 months of imports and servicing external debt, which is well above international adequacy standards of around three months of imports.
 
Improving economic fundamentals in Indonesia helped dampen depreciatory pressures on the rupiah during the fourth quarter of 2013 and continued into January 2014.  On average, the value of the rupiah was Rp12,075 per US dollar in January 2014, down 0.7% but less pronounced than the average decline in December 2013 of 3.74%. Accordingly, the real effective exchange rate was 94.2, which left Indonesian exports relatively more competitive and supported external sector reforms. Activity on the money markets, both the rupiah and foreign exchange money market, continued to perform dynamically with a greater transaction volume and lower risk premium, as indicated by a decrease in credit default swaps (CDS). Such encouraging performance was further linked to measures taken by Bank Indonesia to deepen financial markets, including hedging swaps and interbank repos using mini MRA (Master Repurchase Agreements).
 
The policy response taken by Bank Indonesia with the Government also eased inflationary pressures back to the target corridor of 4.5±1% in 2014 and 4.0±1% in 2015. Headline inflation was 0.75% (qtq) in the final quarter of 2013 or 8.38% (yoy). Inflationary pressures dissipated on all components of inflation, namely core inflation, volatile foods and administered prices. The rate of inflation in January 2014 remained in line historical trends, thereby avoiding undermining the prospect of achieving the inflation target in 2014. Despite exceeding the rate of inflation reported in December 2013, inflation in January 2014 of 1.07% (mtm) varied little from the average for 2008-2013. The increase in the inflation rate in January 2014 was primarily attributable to volatile foods as a result of natural disasters and flooding that subsequently disrupted food production and distribution in a number of regions predominantly on the islands of Java and Sumatera. Meanwhile, core inflation experienced a moderate increase due to, among others, the impact of rupiah depreciation on several commodities like motor vehicles and electronic devices.
 
Measured economic consolidation in Indonesia is supported by well-maintained financial system stability. Banking industry resilience remained solid, while credit risk, liquidity risk and market risk were controlled and capital was resilient. Bank credit growth slowed from 21.9% in November 2013 to 21.4% in December 2013 (or 17.4% if the effect of rupiah depreciation is taken into account) as domestic demand waned and interest rates crept up. The domestic stock market and government securities market remained stable during the reporting quarter despite experiencing a correction as the issue of tapering re-emerged. A rally on the IDX Composite signalled a rebound on the domestic stock market in January 2014. Conversely, the performance of government securities slipped as the yield of tradeable government securities (SBN) increased.
 
In 2014, Bank Indonesia predicts economic stability to return, coupled with more balanced growth, which will further reduce the current account deficit to a healthier level.  Economic growth in 2014 is projected at the lower end of the 5.8%-6.2% range, followed by improvements in the sources of growth as domestic demand decreases and exports expand driven by improvements in the global economy. Additionally, the current account deficit will continue to shrink thanks to the prospect of stronger exports and controlled imports in line with moderating domestic demand. Meanwhile, the rate of inflation will be maintained within its target corridor of 4.5±1%. Against a propitious backdrop of robust economic growth, credit growth is projected in the range of 15-17%, which is consistent with efforts to steer the economy in a more balanced and sound direction.
 
Bank Indonesia will continue to monitor an array of economic risks, globally and domestically, with the potential to disrupt stability and undermine the economic outlook. Globally, risk factors include widespread uncertainty concerning normalisation policy of the Federal Reserve in the US and a potential economic downturn in China. Such risk could destabilise the economic prospects of Indonesia through the financial and trade channels. Domestically, Bank Indonesia will remain vigilant of several risks that could exacerbate inflationary pressures, like disruptions to the supply of food, rising volatile prices and the impact of rupiah depreciation.
 
Assessing the latest developments as well as future economic risks and prospects, on 13th February 2014 Bank Indonesia decided to hold the BI Rate at 7.50%, with the interest rates held on the Lending Facility and Deposit Facility at 7.50% and 5.75% respectively. The policy is consistent with the tight monetary policy stance adopted by Bank Indonesia in order to guide inflation back towards the target of 4.5±1% in 2014 and 4.0±1% in 2015, as well as reduce the current account deficit to a more sustainable level. In addition, Bank Indonesia will also persist with strengthening its monetary and macroprudential policy mix, continue financial market deepening and boost coordination with the Government in order to control inflation and the current account deficit. To this end, Bank Indonesia will continue to advocate using the rupiah for domestic transactions pursuant to the Currency Act and expand hedging instruments for foreign currency transactions. Moreover, Bank Indonesia will also coordinate closely with the Financial Services Authority (OJK) in order to cool off credit growth in line with moderating domestic demand. In addition, Bank Indonesia will remain vigilant of a variety of risks, globally and domestically, as well as ensure anticipatory measures to maintain macroeconomic stability