The global economic recovery is moving forward although overshadowed with uncertainty. Differences have emerged in the pace of global recovery, with growth slackening in advanced economies in contrast to moderate growth in emerging markets. The slowdown in developed nations is also accompanied by considerable uncertainty with manufacturing activity losing steam and consumption held down by high levels of unemployment. Added to this, the yen and euro appreciation against the US dollar has impacted exports from Japan and Europe. The slackening growth in advanced economies is also impacting growth in emerging markets, and particularly export-dependent countries. To resolve this, monetary policy in advanced nations has retained an accommodative bias while emerging market nations are moving forward with policy normalisation. On global financial markets, signs of renewed growth in stock indices were driven in part by signals of the second round monetary stimulus to be launched by developed economies.  This is one of the push factors behind the rush of capital flows into emerging economies, including Indonesia. Added to this are the pull factors of strong economic fundamentals, high returns and improving perceptions of risk in emerging economies.   

At home, the economy is growing at an accelerated rate on the back of consumption and rising investment. Evaluation of the economy's performance and outlook points to overall improvement. Buoyant domestic consumption is supported by a range of factors, including more robust purchasing power, increased support from financing and stronger business and consumer confidence. Alongside this, investment levels are improving in keeping with the launching of policies to support investment activities, improved market perceptions of the economy, increased availability of financing and lower prices for imported capital goods. In other developments, exports have maintained buoyant growth strong despite some slowing in comparison to the previous period, bolstered by high levels of growth in trading partners and the sizeable contribution of resource-based commodities.. An added factor in the upbeat export growth is the mounting trend in commodity prices.  

Indonesia’s balance of payments has recorded yet another estimated surplus. Key to this was the performance of the capital and financial account, marked by heavy inflows of capital into financial instruments such as Indonesian government securities and Bank Indonesia Certificates (SBIs). In the current account, exports continue to forge ahead albeit at a slower pace compared to the preceding month and accompanied by brisk import growth. The steep rise in imports comes in response to buoyant domestic economic activity and the continued high level of exports. Taken together, international reserves at the end of October 2010 reached 91.8 billion US dollars, equivalent to 6.9 months of imports and servicing of official external debt.

During October 2010, the rupiah maintained an appreciating trend buoyed by positive global sentiment towards the Indonesian economy and secure domestic fundamentals. During the period under review, the rupiah averaged Rp 8,929 to the US dollar, representing a gain of 0.6% (mtm). At end-October 2010, the rupiah closed at Rp 8,938 per US dollar, or down 0.15% (ptp) from end-September 2010. The rupiah gains were accompanied by reduced volatility. During October 2010, rupiah volatility averaged 0.1%, down from 0.2% one month earlier.

CPI inflation in October 2010 was marked by milder pressure from volatile foods and administered prices in contrast to mounting pressure in core inflation. Volatile foods underwent deflation in October 2010, partly from corrections in food commodity prices and various transport fares in the wake of the Eid-ul-Fitr festivities. Inflation contributed by administered prices was negligible due to the minimum level of government-announced price increases. However, inflationary pressure in the core category was driven by rising international commodity prices led by gold and sugar.  Taken together, CPI inflation in October 2010 reached 0.06% (mtm) or 5.67% (yoy). n the opinion of Bank Indonesia, potential still exists for future increases in inflationary pressure fuelled by the sustained upward trend in international commodity prices, the unabated anomalies in weather patterns that pose a threat to production and distribution of food staples and surging demand as the end of the year draws near.  

Domestic financial market performance has steadily improved as reflected in the record high in the Indonesian stock index (JCI) and diminishing yield on Indonesian government securities in all tenors. The upswing in financial market performance resulted mainly from the heavy influx of foreign capital inflows. In the area of monetary policy transmission, bank interest rates continue to ease. Rates for bank deposits and credit showed further decline, although at a more modest rate and with a narrowing spread. In the credit channel, credit expansion mounted higher on the strength of consumption credit, despite increased contributions from investment credit and working capital credit. Economic liquidity has also expanded alongside the mounting pace of economic activity. The banking system still carries ample liquidity, with banks facing no difficulties in complying with the 8% statutory reserves requirement.

Financial system stability remained firm with support from the robust condition of the banking sector with regard to various risks and improvement in the banking intermediation function. This is indicated, among others, by the high CAR, now at 16.4%, and the prudent NPLs gross ratio at below 5.0%. Improvement in banking intermediation was reflected in the rate of credit expansion, which climbed to 21.9% (yoy) by end-October 2010. At this level, bank credit expansion is on track with the projected range in Business Plans prepared by banks at 22%-24%. Similarly, credit expansion for the calendar year (ytd) is now positive in all sectors.

Bank Indonesia is confident of the outlook for improving economic conditions, marked by rising GDP growth, inflation at a comfortably safe level in line with the established targeting range and prudently managed financial stability.

Based on an evaluation of the performance and outlook of the economy indicating this improvement, the Bank Indonesia Board of Governors' Meeting on 4 November 2010 decided to maintain the BI Rate at 6.50%. Nevertheless, Bank Indonesia is keeping a close watch on potential for future increases in inflationary pressure. In the opinion of the Board of Governors, the present level of the BI Rate is consistent with achievement of the inflation target and remains conducive to safeguarding financial stability and promoting the necessary banking intermediation for adequate supply-side response to accelerating demand amid heavy inflows of foreign capital and considerable levels of excess liquidity. The Board of Governors stressed the importance of management of economic liquidity as the higher priority. The decision to raise the primary statutory reserve ratio on 1 November 2010 has been implemented smoothly without triggering shocks in banking liquidity. Looking forward, Bank Indonesia will bolster management of liquidity and effectiveness of monetary policy with a mix of monetary and macroprudential policies to manage foreign capital inflows, stabilise the rupiah exchange rate and assure inflation control in line with the established 5% ± 1% target for 2010 and 2011 and 4.5% for 2012. 